<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Asterisk - data science</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/feeds/data-science.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://asterisk.dynevor.org/</id><updated>2020-07-23T21:03:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Data no defense</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/data-no-defense.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-07-23T21:03:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-07-23T21:03:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2020-07-23:/data-no-defense.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;David Shor is a 28-year-old political data analyst who worked for the
2012 Obama campaign. He &lt;a
href="https://twitter.com/davidshor/status/1265998625836019712"&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt;
about a paper with data analysis suggesting that race riots contributed
to Nixon’s victory in 1968:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Post-MLK-assasination race riots reduced Democratic vote share in
surrounding counties by 2%, which was enough to …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;David Shor is a 28-year-old political data analyst who worked for the
2012 Obama campaign. He &lt;a
href="https://twitter.com/davidshor/status/1265998625836019712"&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt;
about a paper with data analysis suggesting that race riots contributed
to Nixon’s victory in 1968:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Post-MLK-assasination race riots reduced Democratic vote share in
surrounding counties by 2%, which was enough to tip the 1968 election to
Nixon. Non-violent protests &lt;em&gt;increase&lt;/em&gt; Dem vote, mainly by
encouraging warm elite discourse and media coverage:
http://www.omarwasow.com/Protests_on_Voting.pdf&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Orthodoxy identified that relaying this analysis was “racist”, and
Shor was &lt;a
href="https://nymag.com/intelligencer/2020/06/case-for-liberalism-tom-cotton-new-york-times-james-bennet.html"&gt;sacked
from his job&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a
href="https://nymag.com/intelligencer/2020/06/white-fragility-racism-racism-progressive-progressphiles-david-shor.html"&gt;publicly
ejected from a progressive mailing list&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="data science"></category></entry><entry><title>Mosteller and data science</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/mosteller-and-data-science.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-07-14T12:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-07-14T12:30:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2020-07-14:/mosteller-and-data-science.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;While chasing down a reference, I came across this paper:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David S. Moore (1993) “A Generation of Statistics Education: An
Interview with Frederick Mosteller”, Journal of Statistics Education,
1:1, DOI: &lt;a
href="https://doi.org/10.1080/10691898.1993.11910453"&gt;10.1080/10691898.1993.11910453&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is an interview with &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frederick_Mosteller"&gt;Frederick
Mosteller&lt;/a&gt; from the end of 1992.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contents …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;While chasing down a reference, I came across this paper:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David S. Moore (1993) “A Generation of Statistics Education: An
Interview with Frederick Mosteller”, Journal of Statistics Education,
1:1, DOI: &lt;a
href="https://doi.org/10.1080/10691898.1993.11910453"&gt;10.1080/10691898.1993.11910453&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is an interview with &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frederick_Mosteller"&gt;Frederick
Mosteller&lt;/a&gt; from the end of 1992.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contents is particularly interesting in contrast to the path that
led me to it. With some friends, I’m in the process of rewriting a &lt;a
href="http://www.resample.com/intro-text-online"&gt;statistics
textbook&lt;/a&gt;. Our book cites Mosteller’s famous introductory
textbook:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frederick Mosteller, R. E. K. Rourke, and G. B. Thomas, Jr. (1970)
“Probability with Statistical Applications”, Second edition.
Addison-Wesley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was interested in the textbook, because it takes the opposite
approach to the one that I am tempted by. Specifically, as the title
implies, the book starts with the mathematics of probability and then
goes on apply this mathematics to statistical problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out, Mosteller had changed his mind about the
probability-first approach to introductory statistics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The history of that [change in approach] is, of course, a little
complicated. I came to Harvard University in the Department of Social
Relations. And there I met many graduate students in anthropology,
clinical and social psychology, and sociology and came up against dozens
and dozens of practical problems. At the same time, I was also working
with Dr. Henry Beecher, an anesthesiologist at the Massachusetts General
Hospital, on problems of anesthetics and analgesics. Consequently, I was
heavily data-oriented, both in the social and medical sciences at that
time, and I had had a great deal of experience in data analysis during
the war. I found that the students were really not very interested in
the logic of statistical analysis. They were eager to get their hands on
tools that would help them solve the problems that they had with their
doctoral or undergraduate dissertations. Most of them had concrete
problems, most of them had data problems, and they were eager to use
statistics to solve their own problems. They were not very interested in
knowing how somebody invented a statistical device, nor did they care to
have it proved to them personally that the method was appropriate or
worked. They were rather eager to get on with doing the analysis and
trying to interpret it, and then bringing it back to patients or theory
of social science, or anthropology, or whatever it might be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, in the classroom as opposed to in the writing of the textbook you
speak of, I found that the students I was teaching didn’t have much
interest in the underpinnings that we in math departments often found
very valuable. So I got to thinking that there might be a way to teach a
course in statistics using primarily data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a lovely sign-off to the interview:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Interviewer] — If I can be a bit unfair, let me put one concluding
question. If you had one short word of advice to offer to teachers of
statistics less experienced than yourself, what would it be?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Mosteller] — Be sure to keep plenty of concrete examples in your
teaching. And if you can hear a pin drop in your classroom, nobody’s
following the lecture (laughter).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content><category term="data science"></category></entry><entry><title>Code is for people</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/code-is-for-people.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-06-07T18:47:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-06-07T18:47:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2020-06-07:/code-is-for-people.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guido_van_Rossum"&gt;Guido van
Rossum&lt;/a&gt; gave &lt;a
href="http://neopythonic.blogspot.com/2016/04/kings-day-speech.html"&gt;something
like a TED talk&lt;/a&gt; on the history of Python. He explains why it is so
important that code is easy to read and understand:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically when you ask a programmer to explain to a lay person what a
programming language is, they will say that …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guido_van_Rossum"&gt;Guido van
Rossum&lt;/a&gt; gave &lt;a
href="http://neopythonic.blogspot.com/2016/04/kings-day-speech.html"&gt;something
like a TED talk&lt;/a&gt; on the history of Python. He explains why it is so
important that code is easy to read and understand:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically when you ask a programmer to explain to a lay person what a
programming language is, they will say that it is how you tell a
computer what to do. But if that was all, why would they be so
passionate about programming languages when they talk among
themselves?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In reality, programming languages are how programmers express and
communicate ideas — and the audience for those ideas is other
programmers, not computers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content><category term="data science"></category></entry><entry><title>Immediate dangers from credulity about artificial intelligence.</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/surgisphere-machine-learning.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-06-07T15:20:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-06-07T15:20:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2020-06-07:/surgisphere-machine-learning.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Surgisphere"&gt;Surgisphere&lt;/a&gt;
is the company that provided the data to two major COVID-19 papers, that
were later retracted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a
href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(20)31324-6/fulltext"&gt;most
shocking of the two retractions&lt;/a&gt; was of a &lt;a
href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(20)31180-6/fulltext"&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;
that appeared to show that patients taking chloroquine and
hydroxychloroquine for COVID-19 were at a greater risk of death. On the
basis …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Surgisphere"&gt;Surgisphere&lt;/a&gt;
is the company that provided the data to two major COVID-19 papers, that
were later retracted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a
href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(20)31324-6/fulltext"&gt;most
shocking of the two retractions&lt;/a&gt; was of a &lt;a
href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(20)31180-6/fulltext"&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;
that appeared to show that patients taking chloroquine and
hydroxychloroquine for COVID-19 were at a greater risk of death. On the
basis of this paper, the World Health Organization stopped ongoing
clinical trials. As the retraction and the Wikipedia page describe, &lt;a
href="https://zenodo.org/record/3862789#.Xtz638bTV0v"&gt;many
scientists&lt;/a&gt; quickly found aspects of the reported data that were
implausible. Surgisphere would not release the data for an independent
audit, so the authors not employed by Surgisphere retracted the
paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the problems with the Surgisphere data was that it was
difficult to see how a company that appeared to have &lt;a
href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/jun/03/covid-19-surgisphere-who-world-health-organization-hydroxychloroquine"&gt;less
than 12 employees&lt;/a&gt;, could possibly have gained access to clinical
data from a significant proportion of hospitals across the world. Even
if they had got such access, how had they dealt with the huge problems
the rest of us have with low quality and coding mismatch that are
typical of digital data in healthcare, even from sophisticated
hospitals?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer, of course, was “advanced machine learning” and
“artificial intelligence”, for which the company had apparently &lt;a
href="https://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/quartzclinical-wins-frost-and-sullivan-best-practices-award-300792202.html"&gt;won
an award&lt;/a&gt; from a company called &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frost_%26_Sullivan"&gt;Frost and
Sullivan&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Surgisphere’s] QuartzClinical cloud-based healthcare data analytics
platform was awarded the 2019 Frost and Sullivan Best Practices Award.
Earning first place in the Machine Learning-Powered Data Analytics
category, QuartzClinical was recognized for its innovative use of big
data, advanced machine learning, and proven real-world applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a
href="https://www.quartzclinical.com/best-practices-award"&gt;their report,
Frost and Sullivan&lt;/a&gt; say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;QuartzClinical’s combination of machine learning technology,
artificial intelligence, and precision analytics can provide results
quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frost &amp;amp; Sullivan’s market research finds that Surgisphere’s
QuartzClinical healthcare data analytics platform connects all data
together through its artificial intelligence and machine learning
engines so that healthcare organization can make better decisions using
benchmark analysis of staff performance. The level 5 machine learning
capability will help Surgisphere’s platform enter the healthcare
industry mainstream in the short term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content><category term="data science"></category></entry><entry><title>The fall and rise of exploratory data analysis</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/the-fall-and-rise-of-exploratory-data-analysis.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-02T10:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-09-02T10:30:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2019-09-02:/the-fall-and-rise-of-exploratory-data-analysis.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;“Exploratory data analysis” (EDA) &lt;span class="citation"
data-cites="tukey1977exploratory"&gt;(Tukey 1977)&lt;/span&gt; is the term that
John W. Tukey gave to the practice of exploring the data with
visualizations and summaries. The careful data analyst should do EDA
before going on to the more familiar mode of making statistical models,
and testing them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember coming …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;“Exploratory data analysis” (EDA) &lt;span class="citation"
data-cites="tukey1977exploratory"&gt;(Tukey 1977)&lt;/span&gt; is the term that
John W. Tukey gave to the practice of exploring the data with
visualizations and summaries. The careful data analyst should do EDA
before going on to the more familiar mode of making statistical models,
and testing them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember coming across these ideas when I was was a PhD student, in
1996. I bought one of Tukey’s books in a second hand bookshop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, I hardly heard about EDA after that. I didn’t use it
myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just came across a 2003 article &lt;span class="citation"
data-cites="curtis2003whatever"&gt;(Curtis and Araki 2003)&lt;/span&gt; recording
its quiet disappearance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this research was to analyze recent statistics
textbooks in the behavioral sciences in terms of their coverage of
exploratory data analysis (EDA) philosophy and techniques. Twenty
popular texts were analyzed. EDA philosophy was not addressed in the
vast majority of texts. Only three texts had an entire chapter on EDA.
None of the authors used the term “confirmatory factor analysis” or
discussed model building or cross-validation. Seven texts contained
references to published work by Tukey, but these references were mainly
for specific techniques, most typically the stem-and-leaf display and
box-and-whiskers plot, which were presented in 15 and 9 texts
respectively. The paper ends with recommendations for integrating EDA
into the fields of psychology and education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EDA has now made a triumphant return, as part of “data science”. As
one example, see the introduction to &lt;a
href="https://r4ds.had.co.nz/introduction.html"&gt;R for data
science&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find this interesting, as part of the pattern that Donoho describes
&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="donoho201550"&gt;(Donoho 2015)&lt;/span&gt;,
of the tendency for academic statistics departments to study clever and
satisfying mathematical models, instead of practical techniques for data
analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps EDA was too hard to teach, or even too hard to do, before we
learned that &lt;a
href="https://matthew-brett.github.io/dsfe/chapters/01/what-is-data-science"&gt;data
analysis must use coding&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="references" class="level3 unnumbered"&gt;
&lt;h3 class="unnumbered"&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent"
role="doc-bibliography"&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-curtis2003whatever" class="csl-entry"
role="doc-biblioentry"&gt;
Curtis, Deborah A, and Cheri J Araki. 2003. &lt;span&gt;“Whatever Happened to
Exploratory Data Analysis? An Evaluation of Behavioral Science
Statistics Textbooks.”&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-donoho201550" class="csl-entry" role="doc-biblioentry"&gt;
Donoho, David. 2015. &lt;span&gt;“50 Years of Data Science.”&lt;/span&gt; In
&lt;em&gt;Princeton &lt;span&gt;NJ&lt;/span&gt;, Tukey Centennial Workshop&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a
href="http://courses.csail.mit.edu/18.337/2015/docs/50YearsDataScience.pdf"&gt;http://courses.csail.mit.edu/18.337/2015/docs/50YearsDataScience.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-tukey1977exploratory" class="csl-entry"
role="doc-biblioentry"&gt;
Tukey, John W. 1977. &lt;em&gt;Exploratory Data Analysis&lt;/em&gt;. Reading, MA,
USA: Ad&lt;span&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;i&lt;span&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;on-Wes&lt;span&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;ey.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="data science"></category></entry></feed>