<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Asterisk - misc</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://asterisk.dynevor.org/</id><updated>2024-09-30T11:49:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Win the election, then hammer disinformation</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/win-election-hammer-disinformation.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-09-30T11:49:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-30T11:49:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2024-09-30:/win-election-hammer-disinformation.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is John Kerry, no less, in a World Economic Forum discussion, no
less, saying that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“It’s really hard to govern today” because of the “problem … of
building consensus”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This because people “self-select where they go for their news”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is “a lot of discussion now about how you …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is John Kerry, no less, in a World Economic Forum discussion, no
less, saying that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“It’s really hard to govern today” because of the “problem … of
building consensus”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This because people “self-select where they go for their news”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is “a lot of discussion now about how you curb those entities”
providing such news.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“… our First Amendment stands as a major block to the ability to be
able to just, you know, hammer [disinformation] out of existence”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The solution is to “win the right to govern” in “this election” so
we can “implement change”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But he worries whether democracies have the ability to implement
these changes “fast enough, big enough”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you, dear voter, want to use your vote to give John Kerry and his
colleagues more power to hammer disinformation, so they can build
consensus, and make it easier to govern?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Questioner: … Could perhaps Secretary Kerry and the panelists could
expand on the role of tackling climate misinformation on the solutions
in the marketplace, ’cause that seems to me that it’s rife out there
both from business investment and consumer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kerry: It’s so tough, everybody is wrestling with that right now. And
I think the dislike of, and anguish over social media, is just growing
and growing and growing. And it’s part of our problem, particularly in
democracies, in terms of building consensus around any issue. It’s
really hard to govern today. You can’t, you know there’s no .. the
referees we used to have to determine what’s a fact, and what isn’t a
fact, the kind of … have been eviscerated to a certain degree. And
people go and people self-select where they go for their news and for
their information, and then you just get into a vicious cycle. So it’s
really, really hard, much harder to build consensus today, than at any
time in the 45-50 years I’ve been involved in this. And there’s a lot of
discussion now about how you curb those entities in order to guarantee
that you’re going to have some accountability on facts, etc. But look,
if people go to only one source, and the source they go to is sick, and,
you know, has an agenda, and they’re putting out disinformation, our
First Amendment stands as a major block to the ability to be able to
just, you know, hammer it out of existence, so what you need, what we
need is to win the ground, win the right to govern, by hopefully having,
winning enough votes that you’re free to be able to implement change.
Now obviously there are some people in this country who are prepared to
implement change in other ways, and that’s really dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interviewer: So you’re questioning really for democracy can survive
unregulated social media?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kerry: I think democracies are deeply, very challenged right now, and
have not proven they can move fast enough or big enough to deal with the
challenges that we are facing. And to me that is part of what this race,
this election is all about — will we break the fever in the United
States, will we bring ourselves back to a regular order as John McCain
used to say, where we’re able to get things done — like a budget — pass
a budget for God’s sake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I travel around the world, I’m pounded by people who say “What’s
the matter with America?” or “Where the hell are you guys going?” And
you all know — I’m not raising anything new — it doesn’t look good, it’s
not working well. And we have to be able to … and I’ve heard this from
leaders of other countries, I won’t mention their names, but some of
them semi-adversarial, and they don’t think our system works very well,
and you look at it and you say, well maybe …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is from the World Economic Forum session &lt;a
href="https://www.weforum.org/events/sustainable-development-impact-meetings-2024/sessions/it-s-not-easy-trading-green"&gt;It’s
not easy trading green&lt;/a&gt;, on September 25, 2024. The text above starts
from around 44.45 in the video.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Love and warmth</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/love-and-warmth.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-09-05T10:31:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-05T10:31:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2024-09-05:/love-and-warmth.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Nietzsche’s publisher, Ernst Schmeitzner, expressed his frustrations
at Wagner and his circle at Bayreuth:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wagner is not even reading Nietzsche’s book … He said to me that
people only read Nietzsche in so far as they cling to him [Wagner] … He
got off some really nasty remarks about Nietzsche …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Nietzsche’s publisher, Ernst Schmeitzner, expressed his frustrations
at Wagner and his circle at Bayreuth:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wagner is not even reading Nietzsche’s book … He said to me that
people only read Nietzsche in so far as they cling to him [Wagner] … He
got off some really nasty remarks about Nietzsche that I shall never
forget … You should have heard in Bayreuth the constant grumbling
against the Jews and “Snap up” (Bismarck). Lucky is he who has nothing
to do with Wagner!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Nietzsche:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quite another sort of man is Nietzsche. … From the outset I was
struck by the love and warmth of this man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both quotes are from “Friedrich Nietzsche: a biography” by Curtis
Cate (2002), p 271.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Candor, commitment, courage and competence</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/candor-commitment-courage-and-competence.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-07-27T11:07:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-07-27T11:07:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2023-07-27:/candor-commitment-courage-and-competence.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;From “National Defense” (1981) by James Fallows, pages 110-111.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an attempt to define more precisely the qualities a leader must
display to produce trust and cohesion among his troops, a team from the
Army War College interviewed majors who had led rifle platoons in
Vietnam several years earlier, asking …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;From “National Defense” (1981) by James Fallows, pages 110-111.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an attempt to define more precisely the qualities a leader must
display to produce trust and cohesion among his troops, a team from the
Army War College interviewed majors who had led rifle platoons in
Vietnam several years earlier, asking them to name the values that
counted in combat. Four qualities stood out, described by Colonel Malone
as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Candor&lt;/em&gt;: It’s more than openness, it’s saying the things that
need to be said without a lot of words, without an under-the-table
agenda, without a lot of Yessir and Nossir. The stakes are too high and
time is too short to screw around with anything but the essence and the
truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The battlefield is the most honest place in the world. The candor of
the battlefield is why cohesiveness forms there so quickly and
permanently, and why lies told there are punished not with gossip but
with action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Commitment&lt;/em&gt;: This is mainly commitment to people, rather than
to an idea. For the soldier, the main commitment is to that “ole buddy,”
and after that to the small group of people in his squad. There’s some
commitment to the larger unit and a little to the nation, but nowhere
near as much as to the buddy and the squad. You see it in the Medal of
Honor winners. They’re mainly men who jump on grenades, and they do it
because they are committed to that small group. You go get your wounded,
because they’re your buddies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Courage&lt;/em&gt;: A guy always has a choice about taking a risk. He
can lie there behind a log and there’s nothing you can do about it. No
one can make him get up. On the battlefield, the risk he must take is a
total-loss risk, and yet, for various reasons, the soldier himself
decides that the total-loss risk is his best choice. Deciding to take
that risk is courage. It is the ultimate definition of a soldier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Courage is contagious. He did it, I can do it. It’s not that they
want to do it, but they will do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Competence&lt;/em&gt;: This is the oldest value on the battlefield. You
can have candor and commitment, but if you are not competent you won’t
survive. On the battlefield, competence establishes the pecking order,
which may or may not correspond to rank or the chain of command,
depending on the competence of those in the chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Risk from artificial intelligence</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/risk-from-artificial-intelligence.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-05-01T17:41:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-05-01T17:41:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2023-05-01:/risk-from-artificial-intelligence.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a
href="https://aiimpacts.org/2022-expert-survey-on-progress-in-ai/#Extinction_from_AI"&gt;AI
impacts survey&lt;/a&gt; records responses from researchers in artificial
intelligence and machine learning. When asked, 50% of the researchers
who responded thought there was a 5% or higher chance of “future AI
advances causing human extinction or similarly permanent and severe
disempowerment of the human species”. 50% gave a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a
href="https://aiimpacts.org/2022-expert-survey-on-progress-in-ai/#Extinction_from_AI"&gt;AI
impacts survey&lt;/a&gt; records responses from researchers in artificial
intelligence and machine learning. When asked, 50% of the researchers
who responded thought there was a 5% or higher chance of “future AI
advances causing human extinction or similarly permanent and severe
disempowerment of the human species”. 50% gave a 10% chance or higher of
“human inability to control future advanced AI systems causing human
extinction or similarly permanent and severe disempowerment of the human
species”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.12852"&gt;another survey of
Natural Language Processing researchers&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About a third (36%) of respondents agree that it is plausible that AI
could produce catastrophic outcomes in this century, on the level of
all-out nuclear war (Q3-4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found the links to these results in &lt;a
href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.00612"&gt;Eight Things to Know about Large
Language Models&lt;/a&gt; by Samual Bowman (2023).&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Achieve!</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/achieve.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-05-01T14:53:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-05-01T14:53:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2023-05-01:/achieve.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I walked home from my job as a lecturer in Birmingham University,
I often noticed this banner on the fences of the all-surface sports
pitches:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="images/discover_develop_achieve.jpg"
alt="Discover. Develop. Achieve." /&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden="true"&gt;Discover. Develop. Achieve.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember recoiling each time I saw it, and thinking, consciously:
“That’s a bit fascist”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A little later, I watched …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I walked home from my job as a lecturer in Birmingham University,
I often noticed this banner on the fences of the all-surface sports
pitches:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="images/discover_develop_achieve.jpg"
alt="Discover. Develop. Achieve." /&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden="true"&gt;Discover. Develop. Achieve.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember recoiling each time I saw it, and thinking, consciously:
“That’s a bit fascist”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A little later, I watched the Amazon Prime series “The Man in the
High Castle”. It imagines a world in which the Nazis and the Japanese
have won the war, and have occupied the United States. Almost exactly
half way through the first episode of the first season, one of the
characters is driving a truck across the Nazi-occupied Midwest. As the
camera follows the truck, it pans across this poster:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="images/achieve.jpg" alt="Achieve!" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden="true"&gt;Achieve!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Novel morality</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/novel-moraltiy.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-09-11T17:40:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-09-11T17:40:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2022-09-11:/novel-moraltiy.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Milan Kundera, in the essay “The Day Panurge No Longer Makes People
Laugh”, published in “Testaments Betrayed” (1993):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the passages wherein Rabelais’s [The Fourth Book] becomes
fully and radically a &lt;em&gt;novel&lt;/em&gt;: that is, a &lt;em&gt;realm where moral
judgment is suspended&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suspending moral judgment is not the immorality …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Milan Kundera, in the essay “The Day Panurge No Longer Makes People
Laugh”, published in “Testaments Betrayed” (1993):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the passages wherein Rabelais’s [The Fourth Book] becomes
fully and radically a &lt;em&gt;novel&lt;/em&gt;: that is, a &lt;em&gt;realm where moral
judgment is suspended&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suspending moral judgment is not the immorality of the novel; it is
its &lt;em&gt;morality&lt;/em&gt;. The morality that stands against the ineradicable
human habit of judging instantly, ceaselessly, and everyone; of judging
before, and in the absence of, understanding. From the view-point of the
novel’s wisdom, that fervid readiness to judge is the most detestable
stupidity, the most pernicious evil. Not that the novelist utterly
denies that moral judgment is legitimate, but that he refuses it a place
in the novel. If you like, you can accuse [Rabelais’s character] Panurge
of cowardice, accuse Emma Bovary, accuse Rastingnac — that’s your
business; the novelist has nothing do do with it [p. 7].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>No fog</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/no-fog.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-09-11T17:33:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-09-11T17:33:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2022-09-11:/no-fog.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is an extended version of a fairly well-known quote from the
essay “Paths in the Fog”, by Milan Kundera, published in his essay
collection “Testaments Betrayed” (1993).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man proceeds in the fog. But when he looks back to judge people of
the past, he sees no fog on their …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is an extended version of a fairly well-known quote from the
essay “Paths in the Fog”, by Milan Kundera, published in his essay
collection “Testaments Betrayed” (1993).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man proceeds in the fog. But when he looks back to judge people of
the past, he sees no fog on their path. From his present, which was
their faraway future, their path looks perfectly clear to him, good
visibility all the way. Looking back, he sees the path, he sees the
people proceeding, he sees their mistakes, but not the fog. And yet all
of them — Heidegger, Mayakovsky, Aragon, Ezra Pound, Gorky, Gottfried
Benn, St.-John Perse, Giono — all were walking in fog, and one might
wonder: who is more blind? Mayakovsky, who as he wrote his poem on Lenin
did not know where Leninism would lead? Or we, who judge him decades
later and do not see the fog that enveloped him?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mayakovsky’s blindness is part of the eternal human condition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for us not to see the fog on Mayakovsky’s path is to forget what
man is, forget what we ourselves are. [p 240]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the same essay:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the conformism of public opinion is a force that sets itself up
as a tribunal, and the tribunal is not there to waste time over ideas,
it is there to conduct the investigations for trials. And as the abyss
of time widens between judges and defendants, it is always a lesser
experience that is judging a greater. The immature sit in judgment on
Céline’s erring ways without realizing that because of these erring
ways, Céline’s novels contain existential knowledge that, if they were
to understand it, could make them more adult. Because therein lies the
power of culture: it redeems horror by transforming it into existential
wisdom. If the spirit of the trial succeeds in annihilating this
century’s culture, nothing will remain of us but a memory of its
atrocities sung by a chorus of children [p. 234]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Postmodern consent</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/postmodern-consent.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-08-09T10:59:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-08-09T10:59:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2022-08-09:/postmodern-consent.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warning : this page refers in a general way to a legal case
involving sex with children. Though the facts are ugly, I believed it
important to document some reactions to the case, as insight into the
world-view of some influential thinkers in 1970s France.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a preface, consider the &lt;a
href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/wicked-and-dangerous-fraud.html"&gt;“irresponsibility …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warning : this page refers in a general way to a legal case
involving sex with children. Though the facts are ugly, I believed it
important to document some reactions to the case, as insight into the
world-view of some influential thinkers in 1970s France.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a preface, consider the &lt;a
href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/wicked-and-dangerous-fraud.html"&gt;“irresponsibility …
of the liberal community”&lt;/a&gt; that James Baldwin complained of during
the McCarthy hearings. Now …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Versailles Affair was a French legal case from 1977 in which
three men &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_petition_against_age_of_consent_laws"&gt;aged
39 to 45&lt;/a&gt;, were prosecuted for having sex with male and female
children aged 13 and 14. Many important intellectuals, including the
founders of post-modernism, publicly supported the immediate release of
these men for time served, and repeal or revision of the law that
allowed prosecution of adults for sex with consenting children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am trying to be as fair as possible to the original sources, by
quoting them at length, with minimal elision, and in context. I’m happy
to hear any suggestions of ways I could do better at that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a translation &lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from the &lt;a
href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Affaire_de_Versailles"&gt;French
Wikipedia page on the Versailles Affair&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1 id="the-case"&gt;The case&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bernard Dejager, Jean-Claude Gallien and Jean Burckhardt were
arrested on October 20, 1973 for having had sexual intercourse with
girls and boys aged 13 and 14. The circumstances were sufficiently
unclear that the investigation lasted more than three years and two
months. The acts allegedly took place at the Camping Club de France de
Meudon, the oldest specialized camping club in France, located in the
Forest of Meudon, which has various groups, including a naturist
group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three men appeared before the Assize Court of Versailles for
“indecent assault without violence on minors aged 15”, which, at the
time, qualified as a crime. Over the course of investigation it seemed
that they were at risk of five to ten years in prison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1
id="matzneffs-op-ed-then-the-petition-of-support-for-the-accused."&gt;Matzneff’s
op-ed, then the petition of support for the accused.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On November 8, 1976, in the newspaper Le Monde, the writer Gabriel
Matzneff published an op-ed in support of the accused, titled “Is love a
crime?, in which he complains bitterly about the lack of support he
received after his appearance on”Apostrophes”, Bernard Pivot’s new TV
show, on September 12, 1975, for which had been severely criticized. He
had received a complaint from a viewer who believed that this
justification for pedophilia had harmed his family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two and a half months later, the three defendants elicited a petition
of support that emphasized the fact that they had been in preventive
detention for three years and two months. The petition is signed by
various public figures: the text affirms that the children suffered “no
violence”, and that they were “consenting”, adding furthermore: “if a
girl of thirteen is entitled to the pill, what is that for?”. The
petition asserts that the tenacity with which the three accused were
being prosecuted was disproportionate: “Three years in prison for
caresses and kisses, that is enough”. The petitioners, who include
well-known intellectuals, consider there is a clear disproportion
between the classification of “crime” that justifies such severity, and
the nature of the alleged offenses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several famous intellectuals were signatories, &lt;a
href="https://archive.wikiwix.com/cache/index2.php?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.lemonde.fr%2Farchives%2Farticle%2F1977%2F01%2F26%2Fa-propos-d-un-proces_2854399_1819218.html#federation=archive.wikiwix.com"&gt;such
as&lt;/a&gt; Gilles Deleuze, Roland Barthes, Simone de Beauvoir, Jean-Paul
Sartre and Félix Guattari.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later, some of the same people signed a &lt;a
href="https://www.dolto.fr/fd-code-penal-crp.html"&gt;petition to the
French parliament&lt;/a&gt; that cites the case as an example of legal excess.
The petition calls for the law to be repealed or changed to make it
legal for children to have sex with adults or other children. Here I
have quoted the beginning and end of the petition:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1
id="open-letter-to-the-commission-for-the-revision-of-the-penal-code-supporting-the-revision-of-some-legislative-instruments-governing-the-relations-between-adults-and-minors"&gt;Open
letter to the Commission for the Revision of the Penal Code supporting
the revision of some legislative instruments governing the relations
between adults and minors&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relationships between children, adolescents and adults are subject to
significant restrictions by law: by the notion of “corruption of minors”
(which can consist of a simple single overnight stay of a minor); by the
general ban on having sexual relations with children under the age of
15; or by the special ban that targets homosexual relations with minors
aged 15 to 18, defined as “immodest or against nature”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The obsolescence of the notions underlying these crimes or
misdemeanors (“modesty”, “nature”), the evolution of mores in a youth
who feel the excesses of fastidious segregation as oppressive, mean that
these legal articles are no more than the instrument of coercion, in
place of a guaranteed right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent case has just clearly shown the disproportion between the
criminal apparatus and the nature of the acts it punishes. After more
than three years of preventive detention, three people accused of
“indecent assault committed or attempted without violence on the person
of children of either sex aged under 15”, acts that the law (article 331
§1 of the Penal Code) qualifies as “crimes”, were sentenced by the Court
of Assizes of Yvelines to 5 years in prison, suspended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The signatories of this letter … believe, more generally, that the
provisions claiming to “protect” children and young people, such as
article 334-1 concerning “the incitement of minors to debauchery”, which
make it possible to charge anyone who “promotes” or “facilitates” sexual
relations between minors, or article 356 concerning the “abuse of
minors”, are, like article 331, increasingly incompatible with the
evolution of our society, justifying harassment and straightforward
police control, and must be repealed, or profoundly modified, in order
to recognize the right of children and adolescents to maintain relations
with persons of their choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 80 signatories included Michel Foucault, Gilles Deleuze, Jacques
Derrida, Roland Barthes, Simone de Beauvoir, Jean-Paul Sartre, Félix
Guattari and Jean-François Lyotard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"
role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;All translation here is a combination of Google
Translate, DeepL, and my own edits for idiomatic English. I’ve given the
French source; if you find somewhere the translation is misleading or
incorrect, let me know.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Going at it blind</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/going-at-it-blind.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-08-06T10:24:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-08-06T10:24:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2022-08-06:/going-at-it-blind.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Charles Marlow is the narrator in Joseph Conrad’s &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heart_of_Darkness"&gt;Heart of
Darkness&lt;/a&gt;. For those of us who remember the film &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apocalypse_Now"&gt;Apocalypse Now&lt;/a&gt;,
Marlow corresponds to Martin Sheen’s character, Captain Willard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this quote from the book, he is talking about soldiers and sailors
from &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romans_in_Sub-Saharan_Africa"&gt;Roman
expeditions to Africa&lt;/a&gt; around …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Charles Marlow is the narrator in Joseph Conrad’s &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heart_of_Darkness"&gt;Heart of
Darkness&lt;/a&gt;. For those of us who remember the film &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apocalypse_Now"&gt;Apocalypse Now&lt;/a&gt;,
Marlow corresponds to Martin Sheen’s character, Captain Willard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this quote from the book, he is talking about soldiers and sailors
from &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romans_in_Sub-Saharan_Africa"&gt;Roman
expeditions to Africa&lt;/a&gt; around the first century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But these chaps were not much account, really. They were no
colonists; their administration was merely a squeeze, and nothing more,
I suspect. They were conquerors, and for that you want only brute
force—nothing to boast of, when you have it, since your strength is just
an accident arising from the weakness of others. They grabbed what they
could get for the sake of what was to be got. It was just robbery with
violence, aggravated murder on a great scale, and men going at it
blind—as is very proper for those who tackle a darkness. The conquest of
the earth, which mostly means the taking it away from those who have a
different complexion or slightly flatter noses than ourselves, is not a
pretty thing when you look into it too much. What redeems it is the idea
only. An idea at the back of it; not a sentimental pretence but an idea;
and an unselfish belief in the idea—something you can set up, and bow
down before, and offer a sacrifice to….”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Text from &lt;a
href="https://www.gutenberg.org/files/219/219-h/219-h.htm"&gt;Heart of
Darkness at Project Gutenberg&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Not convinced</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/not-convinced.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-07-08T17:17:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-07-08T17:17:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2022-07-08:/not-convinced.html</id><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to get a man to understand something, when his salary
depends upon his not understanding it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2017/11/30/salary"&gt;Upton
Sinclair, 1934&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Define Professional</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/define-professional.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-09-11T18:28:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-09-11T18:28:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2021-09-11:/define-professional.html</id><content type="html">&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;em&gt;Professional&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;
A person or state characterized by a lack of charm, imagination, and
independence.
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also see &lt;a href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/not-professional.html"&gt;Not
Professional&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Die Frau mit dem Fagott</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/die-frau-mit-dem-fagott.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-02-06T18:10:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-06T18:10:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2021-02-06:/die-frau-mit-dem-fagott.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just came across &lt;a
href="https://music.apple.com/us/album/die-frau-mit-dem-fagott/1513363794"&gt;this
album&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you didn’t click on the link above, here is the cover
design:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img
src="https://is1-ssl.mzstatic.com/image/thumb/Music113/v4/2a/ee/96/2aee9626-57b4-cf75-c614-fc2ae2e04142/4014513036216_3000.jpg/1000x1000bb.webp" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To clarify, the picture shows the &lt;em&gt;frau&lt;/em&gt; of the album title,
but without her &lt;em&gt;fagott&lt;/em&gt;, which, as you may know, is the German
word for bassoon.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Desire to punish</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/desire-to-punish.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-30T16:35:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-30T16:35:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2020-10-30:/desire-to-punish.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Nietzsche, predicting the age of social media:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But thus do I counsel you, my friends: distrust all in whom the
impulse to punish is powerful!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nietzsche &lt;a
href="https://www.gutenberg.org/files/1998/1998-0.txt"&gt;Thus spake
Zarathustra&lt;/a&gt;, translated by Thomas Common. Chapter 29. The
Tarantulas.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Gothic mask</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/gothic-mask.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-30T16:35:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-30T16:35:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2020-10-30:/gothic-mask.html</id><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hide! Hide! Witch! The good folk come to burn thee! Their keen
enjoyment hid beneath The gothic mask of duty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the opening lines in the story “Hide! Hide! Witch!” By Mark
Clifton and Alex Apostolides, in &lt;a
href="http://www.luminist.org/archives/SF/AST/AST_1953_12_L.jpg"&gt;Astounding
Science Fiction, December 1953&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Why not do it ourselves?</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/i-do-it.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-07-26T13:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-07-26T13:18:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2020-07-26:/i-do-it.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew_Grove"&gt;Andrew Grove&lt;/a&gt;
gives a vivid description of the way that Intel finally summoned the
courage to give up their core business of making computer memory to
concentrate on central processing units.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision was very difficult, and took a relatively long time,
because many in the company had a strong …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew_Grove"&gt;Andrew Grove&lt;/a&gt;
gives a vivid description of the way that Intel finally summoned the
courage to give up their core business of making computer memory to
concentrate on central processing units.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision was very difficult, and took a relatively long time,
because many in the company had a strong commitment to computer memory.
It proved to be necessary because Intel were losing a lot of money
making memory chips as they were failing to compete with Japanese
manufacturers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember a time in the middle of 1985, after this aimless wandering
had been going on for almost a year. I was in my office with Intel’s
chairman and CEO, Gordon Moore, and we were discussing our quandary. Our
mood was downbeat. I looked out the window at the Ferris wheel of the
Great America amusement park revolving in the distance, then I turned
back to Gordon and I asked, “If we get kicked out and the board brought
in a new CEO, what do you think he would do?”. Gordon answered without
hesitation, “He would get us out of memories”. I stared at him, numb,
then said, “Why shouldn’t you and I walk out the door, come back and do
it ourselves?”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/72469/only-the-paranoid-survive-by-andrew-grove"&gt;Only
the Paranoid Survive&lt;/a&gt; by Andrew Grove, 1996, p 89.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Visual Studio Code dines out at expense of other editors</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/editor-dominance.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-07-26T11:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-07-26T11:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2020-07-26:/editor-dominance.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a
href="https://github.com/jupyterlab/team-compass/issues/80"&gt;discussion
about the direction of JupyterLab&lt;/a&gt; led me to some research on the
increasing dominance of Visual Studio Code as a development environment.
Here are some results from the “Development Environment and Tools”
section of the StackOverflow developer survey of &lt;a
href="https://insights.stackoverflow.com/survey/2016#technology-development-environments"&gt;2016&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a
href="https://insights.stackoverflow.com/survey/2017#technologies-and-occupations"&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a
href="https://insights.stackoverflow.com/survey/2018/#development-environments-and-tools"&gt;2018&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a
href="https://insights.stackoverflow.com/survey/2019#development-environments-and-tools"&gt;2019&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ordered the development …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a
href="https://github.com/jupyterlab/team-compass/issues/80"&gt;discussion
about the direction of JupyterLab&lt;/a&gt; led me to some research on the
increasing dominance of Visual Studio Code as a development environment.
Here are some results from the “Development Environment and Tools”
section of the StackOverflow developer survey of &lt;a
href="https://insights.stackoverflow.com/survey/2016#technology-development-environments"&gt;2016&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a
href="https://insights.stackoverflow.com/survey/2017#technologies-and-occupations"&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a
href="https://insights.stackoverflow.com/survey/2018/#development-environments-and-tools"&gt;2018&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a
href="https://insights.stackoverflow.com/survey/2019#development-environments-and-tools"&gt;2019&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ordered the development environments by their rank in 2019. The
numbers are percent of developers using the tool, “select all that
apply”. The editors I’ve listed are the top 11 entries as of 2019, with
a couple of others I’m interested in: Emacs and RStudio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class="header"&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: left;"&gt;Editor&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right;"&gt;2016&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right;"&gt;2017&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right;"&gt;2018&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right;"&gt;2019&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Visual Studio Code&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;24.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;34.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;50.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Visual Studio&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;35.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;38.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;34.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;31.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Notepad++&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;35.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;34.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;34.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;30.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;IntelliJ&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;17.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;23.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;24.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;25.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Vim&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;26.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;27.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;25.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;25.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Sublime Text&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;31.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;31.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;28.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;23.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Android Studio&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;13.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;14.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;19.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;16.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Eclipse&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;22.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;20.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;18.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;14.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;PyCharm&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;6.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;7.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;12.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;13.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Atom&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;12.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;20.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;18.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;13.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;IPython / Jupyter&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;3.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;3.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;7.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;9.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;…&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Emacs&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;5.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;4.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;4.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;4.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;RStudio&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;2.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;1.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;3.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;3.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visual Studio Code grew 26.7% between 2017 and 2019. If I had to
guess, I’d guess that Visual Studio Code is taking users from Sublime
Text (-8 points 2017-2019), Atom (-6.7), Eclipse (-5.6), and Notepad++
(-3.8).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jupyter (+6.1) and PyCharm (+5.7) have been growing fairly quickly
over the same period.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>World divided</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/world-divided.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-07-21T19:53:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-07-21T19:53:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2020-07-21:/world-divided.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The world,” [Dwight Morrow] once wrote to his son, “is divided into
people who do things and people who get the credit. Try, if you can, to
belong to the first class. There’s far less competition.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2013/11/20/work-credit"&gt;Quote
Investigator&lt;/a&gt; tracked this quote down to a 1935 biography of &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dwight_Morrow"&gt;Dwight Morrow …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The world,” [Dwight Morrow] once wrote to his son, “is divided into
people who do things and people who get the credit. Try, if you can, to
belong to the first class. There’s far less competition.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2013/11/20/work-credit"&gt;Quote
Investigator&lt;/a&gt; tracked this quote down to a 1935 biography of &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dwight_Morrow"&gt;Dwight Morrow&lt;/a&gt; by
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harold_Nicolson"&gt;Harold
Nicolson&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the same investigation, &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indira_Gandhi"&gt;Indira Ghandhi&lt;/a&gt;
often expressed the same idea, that she attributed to her &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motilal_Nehru"&gt;grandfather&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some years ago, she recalled what Pandit Motilal Nehru once told her:
“There are two kinds of people, those who do the work, and those who
take the credit. Belong to the first category, since not only do things
get balanced, but there is much less competition.” – 1959 February 8,
The Times of India&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Against data</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/against-data.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-02-04T19:23:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-04T19:23:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2020-02-04:/against-data.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This quote starts on page 117 of &lt;a
href="https://hgs.uhb.nhs.uk/wp-content/uploads/Kennedy-Report-Final.pdf"&gt;the
Kennedy report&lt;/a&gt; on the “rogue surgeon” Ian Paterson:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, there is a deeper point. The pursuit of data might be seen, at
some point, as some sort of displacement activity. Wrestling with the
very human problem of the patient can be postponed …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This quote starts on page 117 of &lt;a
href="https://hgs.uhb.nhs.uk/wp-content/uploads/Kennedy-Report-Final.pdf"&gt;the
Kennedy report&lt;/a&gt; on the “rogue surgeon” Ian Paterson:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, there is a deeper point. The pursuit of data might be seen, at
some point, as some sort of displacement activity. Wrestling with the
very human problem of the patient can be postponed while the technical
issue about data, which the clinician- scientist is more comfortable
with, can be resolved. Indeed, if there is one lesson to be learned from
the many occasions when things appear to have gone wrong in the NHS, it
is that senior managers and doctors who are reluctant to confront what
is actually happening, take refuge in the call for data. The data will
give the answer. And, the next lesson of history, of course, is that
once data is produced, it becomes the focus of argument: is it valid, is
it the right data, is the interpretation valid, is it complete, and so
on: an approach captured in the memorable expression, “dissing the data
is an art form in healthcare”. Time without number, a concern about the
welfare of patients is converted into a crypto-scientific dispute about
numbers. The result is that doing nothing for the time being becomes the
order of the day, justified on the grounds that something (whatever it
is) is not clear from the current data and more data/analysis is
needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel it is worth pointing out that acting without good or reliable
data is an invitation to trial by gossip and mobbing.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Chomsky on class war</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/chomsky-on-class-war.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-11-17T18:57:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-17T18:57:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2019-11-17:/chomsky-on-class-war.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Every now and again, when I’m listening to Chomsky, I burst out
laughing. He is always dry and careful, his delivery rarely changes, and
this makes his more devastating put-downs all the more outrageous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here Chomsky and Foucault are discussing the idea of justice in civil
disobedience:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Foucault: I …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Every now and again, when I’m listening to Chomsky, I burst out
laughing. He is always dry and careful, his delivery rarely changes, and
this makes his more devastating put-downs all the more outrageous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here Chomsky and Foucault are discussing the idea of justice in civil
disobedience:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Foucault: I would simply like to respond to your first sentence, when
you said that, if you didn’t consider the war you wage against the
police, to be just, you wouldn’t wage it. I would simply like to reply
to you in terms of Spinoza and tell you that the proletariat does not
wage war against the ruling class because it considers such a war to be
just. The proletariat wages war against the ruling class because it
wants, for the first time in history, to take power. And because of its
will to overthrow power it considers such a war to be just. One wages
war to win, not because it is just.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chomsky: I don’t personally agree with that. For example, if I could
convince myself that the attainment of power by the proletariat would
lead to a terroristic police state, in which freedom and dignity and
decent human relations would be destroyed, then I wouldn’t want the
proletariat to take power. In fact the only reason for wanting any such
thing, I believe, is because one thinks, rightly or wrongly, that some
fundamental human values will be achieved by that transfer of power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://youtu.be/3wfNl2L0Gf8?t=3351&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Big stuff in Ukraine</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/big-stuff-in-ukraine.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-11-16T10:58:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-16T10:58:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2019-11-16:/big-stuff-in-ukraine.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ukraine embassy official David Holmes on a conversation with Gordon
Sondland, one of the “three amigos” coordinating the Trump / Giuliani
policy on Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holmes is having lunch with Sondland. Sondland has just got off the
phone with Trump, during which Trump was speaking so loudly that Holmes
could hear much …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ukraine embassy official David Holmes on a conversation with Gordon
Sondland, one of the “three amigos” coordinating the Trump / Giuliani
policy on Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holmes is having lunch with Sondland. Sondland has just got off the
phone with Trump, during which Trump was speaking so loudly that Holmes
could hear much of what he said. This conversation between Holmes and
Sondland follows, during which there is a significant disagreement about
what constitutes “big stuff”:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I asked Ambassador Sondland if it was true that the President did not
“give a s—t about Ukraine.” Ambassador Sondland agreed that the
President did not “give a s—t about Ukraine.” I asked why not, and
Ambassador Sondland stated that the President only cares about “big
stuff.” I noted that there was “big stuff” going on in Ukraine, like a
war with Russia, and Ambassador Sondland replied that he meant “big
stuff” that benefits the President, like the “Biden investigation” that
Mr. Giuliani was pushing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/david-holmes-statement-impeachment-inquiry-full-opening-statement"&gt;Holmes’
prepared statement to impeachment inquiry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Computer scientists differ little from the rest of us in “best practice” for software development</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/computer-scientists-are-no-more-likely-to-use-best-practice-for-software-development.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-07-10T16:09:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-07-10T16:09:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2019-07-10:/computer-scientists-are-no-more-likely-to-use-best-practice-for-software-development.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://peerj.com/articles/cs-163"&gt;Towards
computational reproducibility: researcher perspectives on the use and
sharing of software&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;… we conducted a survey to better understand the characteristics of
research software as well as how it is created, used, and shared by
researchers. … Differences between researchers from computer science and
other disciplines related to the knowledge …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://peerj.com/articles/cs-163"&gt;Towards
computational reproducibility: researcher perspectives on the use and
sharing of software&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;… we conducted a survey to better understand the characteristics of
research software as well as how it is created, used, and shared by
researchers. … Differences between researchers from computer science and
other disciplines related to the knowledge of best practices of software
creation and sharing were not statistically significant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article reports the results from a survey for researchers with
the title “Understanding researcher needs and values related to
software”. The authors advertised the survey “through blog posts, social
media, and data- and research-related e-mailing lists and listservs.”.
There is an example advertisement &lt;a
href="https://coffeehouse.dataone.org/2017/01/30/understanding-researcher-needs-and-values-related-to-software"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
The paper notes that “it is likely that our responses were influenced by
our use of computer science and neuroscience-focused e-mail lists.”.
Sure enough, of 215 valid responses, 18% were from “Computer Science”,
14% from Biology, and 13% from Psychology, with fewer responses from
Engineering, Mathematics, Physics and various other fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Section 1 of the survey has the title “Characteristics of Your Code
and Software”, so people who filled in the survey beyond the initial few
questions were probably also authors of software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, there were few large differences in responses from
computer scientists and those from other fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one big difference was that computer scientists were a lot more
likely to “create executables” (82% compared to 50%), perhaps reflecting
a tendency of computer scientists to use compiled languages such as Java
and C++.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computer scientists were a little better than their peers in
responses to most questions about coding and maintenance hygiene.
Relevant questions were “Have you received training in coding
conventions or best practices?” (62% CS vs 52% non-CS); “Do you generate
documentation for your code?” (54% vs 61%); “When you share your code or
software, do you provide information about dependencies?” (90% vs 68%);
“Do you use a version control system (e.g., Git)?” (97% vs 78%).&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Arrogance and inexperience</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/arrogance-and-inexperience.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-07-01T11:23:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-07-01T11:23:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2019-07-01:/arrogance-and-inexperience.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fourth sign of an inexperienced engineer is that they usually
have a lot of pride, a lot of ego, a lot of arrogance. And this is
something that you see in a lot of computer science students coming out
of college for instance, their arrogance is just incredible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/-W_VsLXmjJU?t=479"&gt;Top …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fourth sign of an inexperienced engineer is that they usually
have a lot of pride, a lot of ego, a lot of arrogance. And this is
something that you see in a lot of computer science students coming out
of college for instance, their arrogance is just incredible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/-W_VsLXmjJU?t=479"&gt;Top signs of an
inexperienced engineer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Python is the primary language for data scientists</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/python-is-the-most-in-demand-language.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-07T15:40:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-06-07T15:40:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2019-06-07:/python-is-the-most-in-demand-language.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;See: &lt;a
href="https://towardsdatascience.com/the-most-in-demand-skills-for-data-scientists-4a4a8db896db"&gt;this
analysis of data science job listings&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python is the most in-demand language. The popularity of this
open-source language has been widely observed. It’s beginner friendly,
with many support resources. The vast majority of new data science tools
are compatible with it. Python is the primary language for …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;See: &lt;a
href="https://towardsdatascience.com/the-most-in-demand-skills-for-data-scientists-4a4a8db896db"&gt;this
analysis of data science job listings&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python is the most in-demand language. The popularity of this
open-source language has been widely observed. It’s beginner friendly,
with many support resources. The vast majority of new data science tools
are compatible with it. Python is the primary language for data
scientists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Where is data science on the hype cycle?</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/after-data-science.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-05-30T17:41:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-05-30T17:41:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2019-05-30:/after-data-science.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This post links to some evidence that data science in industry may be
over the peak of the &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hype_cycle"&gt;hype cycle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the hype cycle &lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref"
id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/Gartner_Hype_Cycle.svg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We may be somewhere mid-way between the peak of inflated expectations
and the trough of disillusionment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="where-is-data-science-on-the-hype-cycle-stefan-groschupf"
class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where is data science on the hype cycle …&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This post links to some evidence that data science in industry may be
over the peak of the &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hype_cycle"&gt;hype cycle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the hype cycle &lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref"
id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/Gartner_Hype_Cycle.svg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We may be somewhere mid-way between the peak of inflated expectations
and the trough of disillusionment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="where-is-data-science-on-the-hype-cycle-stefan-groschupf"
class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where is data science on the hype cycle? (Stefan Groschupf)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.dataversity.net/contributors/stefan-groschupf"&gt;Stefan
Groschupf&lt;/a&gt; is a “big data veteran” who co-founded and ran Datameer, a
company that sells a data analytics platform for industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has a Dataversity video blog post from June 2017 on &lt;a
href="https://www.dataversity.net/where-is-data-science-hype-cycle"&gt;Where
is Data Science in the Hype Cycle?&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we’re over the peak. It’s very clear that a lot of companies
realized that this hype of bringing in data scientist teams and building
huge data scientist teams is not the solution for every problem. … We
saw that everybody was very excited and data science solved every
problem including printing money and making the dishes…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="the-credibility-crisis-in-data-science-skipper-seabold"
class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The credibility crisis in data science (Skipper Seabold)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/skipper-seabold-91191774"&gt;Skipper
Seabold&lt;/a&gt; is one of the main authors of the Python &lt;a
href="http://conference.scipy.org/proceedings/scipy2010/pdfs/seabold.pdf"&gt;Statmodels&lt;/a&gt;
package. He is now director of data science at a data science
consultancy company called &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Civis_Analytics"&gt;Civis
Analytics&lt;/a&gt;. He gave a talk at the 2018 PyData conference called &lt;a
href="https://pydata.org/la2018/schedule/presentation/46"&gt;What’s the
Science in Data Science?&lt;/a&gt;, where his abstract starts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand “the credibility revolution in economics” and draw
parallels to the current and coming credibility crisis in data
science&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He then did a &lt;a
href="https://www.datacamp.com/community/podcast/credibility-crisis-in-data-science"&gt;March
2019 interview for the DataCamp podcast&lt;/a&gt;, about “The Credibility
Crisis in Data Science”. His main point was that he was starting to hear
that CEOs with data science teams were wondering what these teams were
for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that I’ve heard just in working here at Civis is like you
say from a CEO of a very large company that every one would know, if I
mentioned who they were. I mean it’s basically saying if I have all
these data scientists, I have hundreds of data scientists and I have no
idea what the fuck they do all day. …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think decision makers don’t know what data scientists are capable
of. They don’t know how to communicate with them what the business needs
are. And I don’t think data scientists necessarily know how to describe
the value of what they are doing in terms that the business can
understand. Or also even focus their efforts on things that will have an
impact for the business, like going out and understanding what it is
that will actually make a difference and then making sure you’re doing
that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="no-data-science-job-titles-by-2029-noah-gift"
class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;No data science job titles by 2029 (Noah Gift)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See this &lt;a
href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/forbestechcouncil/2019/02/04/why-there-will-be-no-data-science-job-titles-by-2029"&gt;Febuary
2019 Forbes article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coming Trough of Disillusionment with data science job titles
will be the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many data science teams have not delivered results that can be
measured in ROI by executives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The excitement of AI and ML has temporary led people to ignore the
basic question: What does a data scientist actually do?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For complex data engineering tasks, you need five data engineers for
every one data scientist.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automation is coming for many tasks data scientists perform,
including machine learning. Every major cloud vendor has heavily
invested in some type of AutoML initiative.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I doubt that the last point is true, unless we reach the surprising
point that it is no longer necessary to understand what the data means
or how the analysis works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="data-science-is-different-now-vicki-boykis" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Data science is different now (Vicki Boykis)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vicki Boykis is a &lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/vickiboykis"&gt;senior manager in data
science and engineering at CapTech&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She wrote a &lt;a
href="https://veekaybee.github.io/2019/02/13/data-science-is-different"&gt;Febrary
2019 blog post&lt;/a&gt; to record her worry that the job title “data
scientist” had been oversold, with the result that there are not enough
jobs for people who have trained to be a “data scientist”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She complains about the hype around “data science”:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, what has not changed is the mass media hype around the
field of data science, which has trumpeted data scientist as the
‘sexiest career of the 21st century’ so many times, that there is now
what I believe to be an important problem that we as a community need to
talk about. That problem is an oversupply of junior data scientists
hoping to enter the industry, and mismatched expectations on what they
can hope to find once they do get that coveted title of “data
scientist.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boykis goes on to list evidence and argument that the market for
people with the job title “data scientist” will shrink, and that there
are too many people training to be a “data scientist”. She calls this a
“data science supply bubble”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is purely anecdotal evidence, so take it with a large grain of
salt. But, based on my own participation as a resume screener, mentor to
data scientists leaving boot camps, interviewer, interviewee, and from
conversations with friends and colleagues in similar positions, I’ve
developed an intuition that the number of candidates per any given data
science position, particularly at the entry level, has grown from 20 or
so per slot, to 100 or more. I was talking to a friend recently who had
to go through 500 resumes for a single opening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="avoiding-the-data-science-hype-bubble-josh-poduska"
class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Avoiding the data science hype bubble (Josh Poduska)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/joshpoduska"&gt;Josh Poduska&lt;/a&gt; is
the chief data scientist at Domino Data Lab. He has a master’s in
applied statistics from Cornell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He wrote a blog post on &lt;a
href="https://blog.dominodatalab.com/avoiding-data-science-hype-bubble"&gt;Avoiding
a Data Science Hype Bubble&lt;/a&gt; in June 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It starts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The noise around AI, data science, machine learning, and deep
learning is reaching a fever pitch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He complains that the field has made little effort to define terms
like “AI”, “machine learning”, or “data science”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has consequences. Two consequences include the creation of a
hype-bubble that leads to unrealistic expectations and an increasing
inability to communicate, especially with non-data science colleagues.
…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The frequent overuse of “AI” when referring to any solution that
makes any kind of prediction has been a major cause of this hype.
Because of frequent overuse, people instinctively associate data science
projects with near perfect human-like autonomous solutions. Or, at a
minimum, people perceive that data science can easily solve their
specific predictive need, without any regard to whether their
organizational data will support such a model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He offers some sober definitions of “AI”, “machine learning” and
“data science”, and concludes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we can all agree that there is too much hype in our industry
today, especially around AI. Each of us has seen how this hype limits
real progress. I argue that a lot of the hype is from misuse of the
terms of data science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="what-should-we-do" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What should we do?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is very surprising to me that a large proportion of people working
in or around data science do not have a good definition for the term,
and do not appear interested to find one. It feels as if the standard
answer to “What is data science?” or “What is AI?” is something close to
“It’s whatever you want it to be.” This must be for the same reasons
that Josh Poduska discusses; “data science” and “AI” are selling well,
for now, so there is little apparent cause to slow down, and consider
whether we are heading in the right direction, and at the right speed. I
think he’s right, that if we don’t do some hard reflection, very soon,
we are going to find ourselves doing a face-plant on gravel as we fall
from the bursting bubble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"
role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Graphic by Jeremykemp at English Wikipedia &lt;a
href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0"&gt;CC BY-SA
3.0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>How do the foundations get built?</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/how-do-the-foundations-get-built.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-05-16T19:26:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-05-16T19:26:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2019-05-16:/how-do-the-foundations-get-built.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This post follows from &lt;a
href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/who-is-building-the-foundations.html"&gt;Who is building
the foundations?&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the title, that last post was about &lt;em&gt;where&lt;/em&gt; the
foundations get built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I am interested the process by which developers start working on
these foundation projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="software-expert-build-or-practitioner-build"
class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Software expert build or practitioner build?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can think of two simple models …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This post follows from &lt;a
href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/who-is-building-the-foundations.html"&gt;Who is building
the foundations?&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the title, that last post was about &lt;em&gt;where&lt;/em&gt; the
foundations get built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I am interested the process by which developers start working on
these foundation projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="software-expert-build-or-practitioner-build"
class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Software expert build or practitioner build?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can think of two simple models:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Software expert build - or “Here, try this thing I built.” The
developer has an idea for a library that they believe will be useful for
people doing data analysis. They build it, and then go to find
users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practitioner build - or “I need this thing, so I’m going to build
it.” The developer has some data they need to analyze, or other work
they need to do, or do more efficiently. They build the library to do
that work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, a entirely new language is likely to be in the Software
Expert Build category, because a working scientist or data analyst is
unlikely to have the time or expertise to build a language. I presume
that domain-specific libraries, like &lt;a
href="https://www.astropy.org"&gt;Astropy&lt;/a&gt;, will usually come from the
“Practitioner Build” group, where development gives more immediate
benefit for work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put the distinction another way - what matters in open-source
development: having a hard data analysis problem; or being expert in
software development; or do we need both (to get started)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="some-references-that-came-to-mind" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Some references that came to mind&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “Practitioner Build” model follows Eric Raymond’s first lesson
from &lt;a
href="http://www.catb.org/~esr/writings/cathedral-bazaar/cathedral-bazaar/ar01s02.html"&gt;The
Cathedral and the Bazaar&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every good work of software starts by scratching a developer’s
personal itch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our question is - what happens if the person with the itch is not
(yet) a developer. Does that person need a developer to come and help?
Or do they teach themselves, and become a developer?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is some discussion of this problem in the paper &lt;a
href="https://www.cs.umd.edu/~hollings/papers/ieee-sw-2008.pdf"&gt;Understanding
the High-Performance Computing Community: A Software Engineer’s
Perspective&lt;/a&gt;. The paper describes the results of interaction between
software engineers and scientists using large clusters to simulate
“physical phenomena such as earthquakes, global climate change or
nuclear reactions”. The message I took from the paper was that Software
Experts often suggest solutions that Practitioners will not use, often
with good reason:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our aim in this paper is to distill our experience about how software
engineers can productively engage the HPC community. Several software
engineering practices generally considered good ideas in other
development environments are quite mismatched to the needs of the HPC
community. We found that keys to successful interactions include a
healthy sense of humility on the part of software engineering
researchers and the avoidance of assumptions that software engineering
expertise applies equally in all contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="why-it-matters" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why it matters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distinction between Software Expert Build and Practitioner Build
is important, because the models have different implications for funding
and support. If the most fruitful development comes from Software Expert
Build, then we can follow a traditional path by finding and funding
experts with good ideas. If Practitioner Build has been more effective,
we will need more imagination, because the practitioner builders will be
harder to find, before most of the work is done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="relevant-data-from-scientific-python-libraries"
class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Relevant data from scientific Python libraries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is to collate some data on the distinction between Software
Expert Build and Practitioner Build, for the three most fundamental
libraries in scientific Python: Numpy; Scipy and Matplotlib. Numpy is
the base layer that implements the array object in Python, and seems
close to a language on the spectrum above. Scipy is a collection of
libraries that build on Numpy, and is therefore closer to the domain
libraries. Matplotlib is the standard 2D plotting library for
Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also done some more superficial analysis of another three
important projects in the scientific Python world: IPython / Jupyter
(interactive prompt / Notebook interface); Pandas (base library for data
science); and Statsmodels (statistical models).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have two sources of data to look at the Software Expert /
Practitioner build distinction. The first are brief early histories of
each project, from the main authors. Was the project driven by a good
idea, in search of work to do, or was it driven by work that needed
doing? I have histories for all the projects above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second source of data is the educational background of the
contributors. In the case of Software Expert Build, I expect
contributors to have training in computer science in general, and
algorithm design / software engineering in particular. I have these data
for Numpy, Scipy and Matplotlib. I didn’t have time to research the
backgrounds of the developers for the other libraries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="abbreviations" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abbreviations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are abbreviations I will use for the tables below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Eng.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Engineering&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Sci.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Science&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Sys.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Systems&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;EE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Electrical Engineering&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;EECS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Electrical Engineering and Computer Science&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;CS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Computer Science&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;C Sys. Eng.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Computer and Systems Engineering&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Comp. Biol.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Computational Biology&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="numpy" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Numpy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim_Hugunin"&gt;Jim Hugunin&lt;/a&gt;
was a major author of &lt;em&gt;Numeric&lt;/em&gt;, the package that later became
Numpy. He summarizes the origins of Numeric in &lt;a
href="http://hugunin.net/story_of_jython.html"&gt;the story of
Jython&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story of Jython begins with the pain of finishing my master’s
thesis at MIT. In that thesis I fabricated, measured, and analyzed
superconductor-semiconductor junctions as a potential building block for
a quantum computer. For analyzing the measurements and comparing them
with theory (the Bogoliubov-deGennes equations) I used matlab
extensively. Matlab is a wonderful language for a wide range numerical
analyses; however, it is a terrible language in which to do anything
else. In order to overcome its shortcomings, I eventually cobbled
together a hodge-podge of C, Python and matlab code to produce my final
results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I knew there had to be a better way of doing this. After finishing my
thesis, I started to work on an extension to Python to support numeric
analysis as naturally as matlab does, without sacrificing any of the
power of Python as a rich general-purpose programming language. This was
the first project where I discovered the power of a collaborative open
source community. The contributions of Jim Fulton, David Ascher, Paul
DuBois, Konrad Hinsen, and many others made that project much more
successful than it could ever have been as an isolated endeavor. …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://legacy.python.org/workshops/1995-12/papers/hugunin.html"&gt;Elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;
Hugunin notes that Numeric “is based on Jim Fulton’s original
implementation of a matrix object as a container class.” He links to the
&lt;a
href="https://web.archive.org/web/19970606192854/http://www.python.org/workshops/1995-05/extModulesNotes.html"&gt;then-current
list of Python extension modules&lt;/a&gt; that contains a description of
Fulton’s “Fortran Matrix extension”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the educational backgrounds of the Numpy founding fathers
that Hugunin names above:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class="header"&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: left;"&gt;Bachelor’s&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: left;"&gt;Master’s&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: left;"&gt;PhD&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jim Hugunin &lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;EE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;EECS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jim Fulton &lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Civil Eng.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Sys. Eng.,&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Software Sys.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Eng.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;David Ascher &lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Cognitive Sci.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Paul DuBois &lt;a href="#fn4" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref4"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Math&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Konrad Hinsen &lt;a href="#fn5" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref5"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although Hugunin was studying Electrical Engineering and Computer
Science when he was writing Numeric, his description above gives the
impression of an engineer building a machine that happened to be a
computer, where the analysis problems arose from the task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fulton &lt;a href="#fn6" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref6"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has a background in civil and
systems engineering. At the time Numeric was starting, he was working at
the US Geological Survey. He records his roles as “Data analysis,
hydrologic modeling, and development and support of data analysis
tools.”, so this qualifies him as a practitioner. He was also studying
for an MS in software systems engineering, making him a rare case of a
trained practitioner and formally trained software engineer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the educational backgrounds for the top 10 authors of Numpy,
by number of commits, from Git commit &lt;code&gt;4b6b29afc&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class="header"&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Commits&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: left;"&gt;Bachelor’s&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: left;"&gt;Master’s&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: left;"&gt;PhD&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Charles Harris &lt;a href="#fn7" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref7"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4169&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Math&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Travis Oliphant &lt;a href="#fn8" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref8"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2065&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;EECS, Math&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;EECS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Biomedical Eng.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;David Cournapeau &lt;a href="#fn9" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref9"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1525&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;EE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;CS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pearu Peterson &lt;a href="#fn10" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref10"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1061&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eric Wieser &lt;a href="#fn11" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref11"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;935&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Eng.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pauli Virtanen &lt;a href="#fn12" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref12"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;762&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mark Wiebe &lt;a href="#fn13" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref13"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;759&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;CS / Math&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Julian Taylor &lt;a href="#fn14" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref14"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;745&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ralf Gommers &lt;a href="#fn15" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref15"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;619&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Matti Picus &lt;a href="#fn16" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref16"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;516&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Agricultural Eng.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the table above, contributors with specific education in
computer science are Travis Oliphant (bachelor’s and master’s degrees
are in Electrical and Computer Engineering), David Cournapeau (PhD in
Informatics), and Mark Wiebe (bachelor’s in computer science and
math).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oliphant’s master’s thesis was applied work on “New Methods for
Scatterometry based Wind Estimation”. &lt;a
href="http://hdl.handle.net/2433/126467"&gt;Cournapeau’s thesis&lt;/a&gt; was
also applied work on speech processing and machine learning. I think
both are examples of practitioners who became developers in response to
the needs of their analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark Wiebe had a lot of experience in software engineering before he
began to work on Numpy (see &lt;a href="#fn17" class="footnote-ref"
id="fnref17" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). His is an
interesting case, in that he made substantial contributions to Numpy,
including the widely used &lt;code&gt;einsum&lt;/code&gt; function, but he is also
the only contributor that I can remember who had a &lt;a
href="https://github.com/numpy/numpy/pull/297"&gt;large amount of their
code pulled out of the main Numpy repository&lt;/a&gt; because the community
could not agree on the changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="scipy" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Scipy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the “Origins of Numpy” chapter in &lt;a
href="http://web.mit.edu/dvp/Public/numpybook.pdf"&gt;Guide to Numpy&lt;/a&gt; by
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Travis_Oliphant"&gt;Travis
Oliphant&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1998, as a graduate student studying biomedical imaging at the
Mayo Clinic in Rochester, MN, I came across Python and its numerical
extension (Numeric) while I was looking for ways to analyze large data
sets for Magnetic Resonance Imaging and Ultrasound using a high-level
language. …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I progressed with my thesis work, programming in Python was so
enjoyable that I felt inhibited when I worked with other programming
frameworks. As a result, when a task I needed to perform was not
available in the core language, or in the Numeric extension, I looked
around and found C or Fortran code that performed the needed task,
wrapped it into Python (either by hand or using SWIG), and used the new
functionality in my programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By operating in this need-it-make-it fashion I ended up with a
substantial library of extension modules that helped Python + Numeric
become easier to use in a scientific setting. …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I finished my Ph.D. in 2001, Eric Jones (who had recently
completed his Ph.D. at Duke) contacted me because he had a collection of
Python modules he had developed as part of his thesis work as well. He
wanted to combine his modules with mine into one super package. Together
with Pearu Peterson we joined our efforts, and SciPy was born in
2001.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We already know the educational background of Oliphant and Peterson
from the Numpy table above. &lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ericjones2/"&gt;Eric Jones&lt;/a&gt; has a BSE
in Mechanical Engineering and a PhD in Electrical Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the top 10 contributors to Scipy (as of
&lt;code&gt;4d9467958&lt;/code&gt;) by number of commits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class="header"&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Commits&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: left;"&gt;Bachelor’s&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: left;"&gt;Master’s&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: left;"&gt;PhD&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pauli Virtanen &lt;a href="#fn18" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref18"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2886&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ralf Gommers &lt;a href="#fn19" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref19"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;19&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2478&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Evgeni Burovski &lt;a href="#fn20" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref20"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;20&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1077&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Physics, Math&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Travis Oliphant &lt;a href="#fn21" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref21"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;21&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;977&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;EECS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;EECS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Biomedical Eng.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;David Cournapeau &lt;a href="#fn22" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref22"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;22&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;820&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;EE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;CS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Warren Weckesser &lt;a href="#fn23" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref23"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;23&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;756&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;C Sys. Eng.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;C Sys. Eng.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Math&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Alex Griffing &lt;a href="#fn24" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref24"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;604&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Math&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Bioinformatics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pearu Peterson &lt;a href="#fn25" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref25"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;25&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;504&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nathan Bell &lt;a href="#fn26" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref26"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;26&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;375&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;CS, Math&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;CS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;“Endolith” &lt;a href="#fn27" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref27"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;27&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;362&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Sci., EE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scipy top contributors with computer science training are Oliphant,
Cournapeau, Weckesser and Bell. I have already discussed Oliphant and
Cournapeau above; I think both are best described as practitioners who
became developers. Weckesser has a Bachelor’s and a Master’s in Computer
and System Engineering; his publication list &lt;a href="#fn28"
class="footnote-ref" id="fnref28" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;28&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
suggests he has a longstanding interest in numerical software. &lt;a
href="https://scholar.google.co.uk/citations?user=BA-ae2MAAAAJ"&gt;Bell’s
Google Scholar page&lt;/a&gt; shows he has many papers at the interface of
software and numerical methods. I think both Weckesser and Bell can
reasonably be classified as Software Experts who are also Practitioners
(of numerical methods).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="matplotlib" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Matplotlib&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://matplotlib.org/users/history.html"&gt;history of
Matplotlib&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_D._Hunter"&gt;John Hunter&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For years, I used to use MATLAB exclusively for data analysis and
visualization. MATLAB excels at making nice looking plots easy. When I
began working with EEG data, I found that I needed to write applications
to interact with my data, and developed an EEG analysis application in
MATLAB. As the application grew in complexity, interacting with
databases, http servers, manipulating complex data structures, I began
to strain against the limitations of MATLAB as a programming language,
and decided to start over in Python. Python more than makes up for all
of MATLAB’s deficiencies as a programming language, but I was having
difficulty finding a 2D plotting package …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding no package that suited me just right, I did what any
self-respecting Python programmer would do: rolled up my sleeves and
dived in. …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Hunter is also one of the top 10 contributors to Matplotlib by
commits, as of commit &lt;code&gt;a58f1c613&lt;/code&gt;. Here is the full list:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class="header"&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Commits&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: left;"&gt;Bachelor’s&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: left;"&gt;Master’s&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;PhD&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Thomas Caswell &lt;a href="#fn29" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref29"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;29&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4309&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Physics, Math&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Michael Droettboom &lt;a href="#fn30" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref30"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;30&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3918&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;CS, Music&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Music&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;John Hunter &lt;a href="#fn31" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref31"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;31&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2145&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Politics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Neurobiology&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Eric Firing &lt;a href="#fn32" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref32"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;32&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1810&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Earth Sci.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Oceanography&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Antony Lee &lt;a href="#fn33" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref33"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;33&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1680&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Eng.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jody Klymak &lt;a href="#fn34" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref34"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;34&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1073&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Math, Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Oceaongraphy&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Oceanography&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;David Stansby &lt;a href="#fn35" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref35"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;35&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1066&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Natural Sci.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Elliott Sales de Andrade &lt;a href="#fn36" class="footnote-ref"
id="fnref36" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;36&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;960&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Eng.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jens Hedegaard Nielsen &lt;a href="#fn37" class="footnote-ref"
id="fnref37" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;37&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;856&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Physics&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nelle Varoquaux &lt;a href="#fn38" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref38"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;38&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;806&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;CS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Math&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Comp. Biol.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not many Matplotlib contributors have a computer science
background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Droettboom &lt;a href="#fn39" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref39"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;39&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has a double major in music and
computer science, and a masters in music / computer music research. It
is difficult to tell if he had specific interest in software engineering
or algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Varoquaux &lt;a href="#fn40" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref40"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;40&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has a bachelor’s in CS, but has
since worked in math and science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="pandas" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Pandas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pandas is the fundamental library for most data science tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have not analyzed the top contributors. Here is a short early
history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wes McKinney created Pandas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I studied theoretical mathematics at MIT (graduating in late 2006)
…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From August 2007 to July 2010, I worked on the front office quant
research team at AQR Capital Management … I started building pandas on
April 6, 2008, as part of a skunkworks effort to reproduce some
econometric research in Python. (from &lt;a
href="https://wesmckinney.com/pages/about.html"&gt;McKinney’s blog
bio&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He gives more detail in a &lt;a
href="https://www.pythonpodcast.com/wes-mckinney-python-for-data-analysis-episode-203"&gt;podcast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a mathematics background and I didn’t do a lot of programming
in the past. …. I really didn’t start programming until much later in
life because I realized at some point that I needed to program in order
to be useful. In my first job in AQR capital management … I was struck
by how difficult it was to go about very basic data analysis problems. …
it felt that there was a disconnect between ability of your mind and
your brain to think about what you want do with the data and the actual
tools to do what you want. … I got really interested in building tools
for myself to be more productive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="ipython-jupyter" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;IPython / Jupyter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://fperez.org/personal.html"&gt;Fernando Pérez&lt;/a&gt; created
IPython in 2001. IPython gradually developed into Jupyter, the widely
used interactive notebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the website above, Fernando gives his biography as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was born in Medellín, Colombia, where I did my undergraduate
studies in Physics at the Universidad de Antioquia. From there I moved
to Boulder, Colorado, where I completed my PhD in particle physics,
before spending a few years as a post-doc in Applied Mathematics. In
2008 I moved to the San Francisco Bay Area, where I now work at UC
Berkeley, on research involving algorithms and tool development in
neuroimaging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He is now a professor of statistics at UC Berkeley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fernando wrote a &lt;a
href="http://blog.fperez.org/2012/01/ipython-notebook-historical.html"&gt;history
of IPython and the Notebook&lt;/a&gt;. The quotes in this section are from
that blog post, unless I list another source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s go back to the beginning: when I started IPython in late 2001,
I was a graduate student in physics at CU Boulder. … … the natural flow
of scientific computing pretty much mandates a solid interactive
environment, so while other Python users and developers may like having
occasional access to interactive facilities, scientists more or less
demand them. … We continued slowly working on IPython, … By that point
Brian Granger and Min Ragan-Kelley had come on board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://us.pycon.org/2017/speaker/profile/2091"&gt;Ragan-Kelley&lt;/a&gt;
has a “PhD in Applied Science &amp;amp; Technology, with an emphasis in
computational plasma physics”. &lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/brian-granger-b9998662"&gt;Granger&lt;/a&gt;
has a bachelor’s in Engineering Physics, and PhD in Physics. At the time
he joined IPython, in &lt;a
href="https://ipython.org/_static/sloangrant/sloan-grant.html"&gt;2004&lt;/a&gt;,
he was an assistant professor in Physics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where early 2010 found us … I read an article about [the
messaging library] ZeroMQ … It became clear that we had the right tools
to build a two-process implementation of IPython that could give us the
‘real IPython’ but communicating with a different frontend, and this is
precisely what we wanted for cleaner parallel computing, multiprocess
clients and a notebook. … In October 2010 James Gao (a Berkeley
neuroscience graduate student) wrote up a quick prototype of a web
notebook, demonstrating again that this design really worked well and
could be easily used by a completely different client. … And finally, in
the summer of 2011 Brian took James’ prototype and built up a fully
working system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ipython.org/_static/sloangrant/sloan-grant.html"&gt;A
2012 grant application&lt;/a&gt; describes the process by which Pérez, Granger
and Kelley trained themselves as developers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we were all trained as physicists without any software
engineering education, in our interaction with the world of open source
developers we have learned and adopted rigorous software engineering
practices that we follow to ensure IPython remains a robust and
high-quality project even as it grows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="statsmodels" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Statsmodels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are notes for the early history of the Statmodels project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skipper Seabold &lt;a href="#fn41" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref41"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;41&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; started Statsmodels proper, as a &lt;a
href="https://scipystats.blogspot.com/2009/04/getting-started-with-gsoc-and-scipy.html"&gt;Google
Summer of Code project&lt;/a&gt;, in collaboration with Josef Perktold &lt;a
href="#fn42" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref42"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;42&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.datacamp.com/community/blog/credibility-crisis-in-data-science"&gt;Seabold
was interviewed in a recent podcast&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My background, my major up until my last year of undergrad was poetry
writing. So I could not have been further from math and data science and
programming. I switched over to studying economics. Ended up going to
grad school for econ. Really liked econometrics, anyway, we got into our
math econ kind of boot camp and first math econ class and it was taught
in Python. … It really helped solidify the stuff I was working on. I
felt like I didn’t really understand it until I could code it. And once
I could code it I was like, “Oh sure I totally understand this and now
can program and speak confidently about it I guess.” … I jumped in, and
the thing that was really helpful was there was a problem out there that
I needed to solve. I needed to be able to run an OLS regression, get the
results out of the regression in a way that was easily understandable,
build a user interface. I didn’t know the first thing about programming,
but I had some good and patient mentors and kind of co-developers along
the way. I learned a ton from the open source community. Just by kind
of, honestly, failing in public, flailing in public, making pull
requests and having people take the time out of their day to spend hours
reading your code and suggest how to be a better programmer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the &lt;a
href="https://conference.scipy.org/proceedings/scipy2010/pdfs/seabold.pdf"&gt;Statsmodels
Scipy conference paper&lt;/a&gt; by Seabold and Perktold:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;… statsmodels was started by Jonathan Taylor, a statistician now at
Stanford, as part of SciPy under the name &lt;em&gt;models&lt;/em&gt;. Eventually,
&lt;em&gt;models&lt;/em&gt; was removed from SciPy and became part of the NIPY
neuroimaging project in order to mature. Improving the models code was
later accepted as a SciPy-focused project for the Google Summer of Code
2009 and again in 2010. It is currently distributed as a SciKit, or
add-on package for SciPy. The current main developers of statsmodels are
trained as economists with a background in econometrics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taylor wrote the original code to implement analysis of brain imaging
data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perktold &lt;a href="#fn43" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref43"
role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;43&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is an economist. He has a PhD in
economics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="conclusion" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In very brief summary, the histories of the various projects here are
striking in the clarity with which they describe the process where
practitioners start with an analysis problem, then build the solution. I
would say they give very strong evidence for the Practitioner Build
model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The analysis of contributor backgrounds is a little more ambiguous.
There are some major contributors, particularly in Scipy, that do have a
strong prior background in software engineering. The large majority of
top contributors, and project founders, did not have this background. A
background in physical sciences is common, but there are many
contributors with a math background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, these data give strong preference for the Practitioner
Builder model. Unless something has changed, we have a difficult
problem, in trying to support the practitioners who will build the next
generation of libraries. If these histories are still typical, by the
time we find them, most of the work will have been done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"
role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jimhugunin"&gt;Hugunin’s LinkedIn
page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jimfulton"&gt;Fulton’s
LinkedIn page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/davidascher"&gt;Ascher’s LinkedIn
page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn4"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://pfdubois.com/bio.html"&gt;Dubois’ web
pages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref4" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn5"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0330-9428"&gt;Hinsen’s
Orchid page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref5" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn6"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jimfulton"&gt;Fulton’s
LinkedIn page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref6" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn7"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.blog.pythonlibrary.org/2017/12/04/pydev-of-the-week-charles-r-harris"&gt;Harris
interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref7" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn8"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/teoliphant"&gt;Oliphant’s LinkedIn
page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref8" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Cournapeau"&gt;Cournapeau’s
Wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref9" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn10"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://cens.ioc.ee/~pearu"&gt;Peterson’s web
page&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/pearu-peterson-8877bb162"&gt;Peterson’s
LinkedIn page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref10" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn11"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/eric-wieser-2085445b"&gt;Wieser’s
LinkedIn page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref11" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn12"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/pauli-virtanen-627139a"&gt;Virtanen’s
LinkedIn page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref12" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn13"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mark-wiebe-88738b2"&gt;Wiebe’s LinkedIn
page&lt;/a&gt;; it’s not clear whether he has a post-graduate degree. Bachelor
majors listed in &lt;a
href="https://umanitoba.ca/faculties/science/about/1262.html"&gt;UManitoba
page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref13" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn14"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reply to personal email.&lt;a href="#fnref14"
class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn15"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ralf-gommers-97317b4/"&gt;Gommers’
LinkedIn page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref15" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn16"&gt;&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a
href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fRTSUpzpTVg"&gt;Pincus’ Youtube
presentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref16" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn17"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mark-wiebe-88738b2"&gt;Wiebe’s LinkedIn
page&lt;/a&gt;; it’s not clear whether he has a post-graduate degree. Bachelor
majors listed in &lt;a
href="https://umanitoba.ca/faculties/science/about/1262.html"&gt;UManitoba
page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref17" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn18"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/pauli-virtanen-627139a"&gt;Virtanen’s
LinkedIn page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref18" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn19"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ralf-gommers-97317b4/"&gt;Gommers’
LinkedIn page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref19" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn20"&gt;&lt;p&gt;CV via &lt;a
href="https://www.hse.ru/en/org/persons/190080844"&gt;Burovski’s
webpage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref20" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn21"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/teoliphant"&gt;Oliphant’s LinkedIn
page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref21" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn22"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/teoliphant"&gt;Oliphant’s LinkedIn
page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref22" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn23"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180510010523/http://www.warrenweckesser.net:80/menu_cv.html"&gt;Archive
of Weckesser’s webpage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref23" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn24"&gt;&lt;p&gt;See biography in &lt;a
href="https://repository.lib.ncsu.edu/bitstream/handle/1840.16/7496/etd.pdf"&gt;Griffing’s
2012 thesis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref24" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn25"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://cens.ioc.ee/~pearu"&gt;Peterson’s web
page&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/pearu-peterson-8877bb162"&gt;Peterson’s
LinkedIn page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref25" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn26"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/nathan-bell-65963915"&gt;Bell’s LinkedIn
page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref26" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn27"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.codementor.io/endolith"&gt;Endolith’s
Codementor page&lt;/a&gt;; he has a BSEE degree.&lt;a href="#fnref27"
class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn28"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180510010523/http://www.warrenweckesser.net:80/menu_cv.html"&gt;Archive
of Weckesser’s webpage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref28" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn29"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/tcaswell"&gt;Caswell’s LinkedIn
page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref29" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn30"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mdboom"&gt;Droettboom’s LinkedIn
page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref30" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn31"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Personal email in 2005&lt;a href="#fnref31"
class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn32"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="http://www.soest.hawaii.edu/oceanography/faculty/firing.html"&gt;Firing’s
work web page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref32" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn33"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2193-5369"&gt;Lee’s
ORCID page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref33" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn34"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="http://valdez.seos.uvic.ca/~jklymak/pdfs/KlymakCv.pdf"&gt;Klymak’s
work pages CV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref34" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn35"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1365-1908"&gt;Stansby’s ORCID page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a
href="#fnref35" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn36"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7310-8942"&gt;Sales
de Andrade’s ORCID page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref36" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn37"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jens-hedegaard-nielsen-16328151"&gt;Nielsen’s
LinkedIn page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref37" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn38"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/nelle-varoquaux-63250a34"&gt;Varoquaux’
LinkedIn page&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a
href="https://bids.berkeley.edu/people/nelle-varoquaux"&gt;BIDS
biosketch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href="#fnref38" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn39"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mdboom"&gt;Droettboom’s LinkedIn
page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref39" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn40"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/nelle-varoquaux-63250a34"&gt;Varoquaux’
LinkedIn page&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a
href="https://bids.berkeley.edu/people/nelle-varoquaux"&gt;BIDS
biosketch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href="#fnref40" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn41"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/skipper-seabold-91191774"&gt;Seabold’s
LinkedIn page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref41" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn42"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/josef-perktold-josef-pktd-9a23b316"&gt;Perktolds’s
LinkedIn page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref42" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn43"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/josef-perktold-josef-pktd-9a23b316"&gt;Perktolds’s
LinkedIn page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref43" class="footnote-back"
role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Learning and Twitter</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/learning-and-twitter.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-04-17T10:21:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-04-17T10:21:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2019-04-17:/learning-and-twitter.html</id><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We have to create a healthy contribution to the network and a
healthy conversation. On Twitter right now you don’t necessarily walk
away feeling you learned something.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From an &lt;a
href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-47955820"&gt;interview with
Twitter co-founder Jack Dorsey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Worse is better</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/worse-is-better.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-04-15T11:35:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-04-15T11:35:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2019-04-15:/worse-is-better.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a
href="http://www.modernperlbooks.com/mt/2012/12/the-implementation-of-perl-5-versus-perl-6.html"&gt;blog
post on Perl 6&lt;/a&gt; led me to the description of &lt;a
href="https://www.jwz.org/doc/worse-is-better.html"&gt;Worse is better
philosophy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get the impression this idea is relatively famous, but I had not
come across it before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A summary might be, that successful systems often pass rough edges of
the design to the user …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a
href="http://www.modernperlbooks.com/mt/2012/12/the-implementation-of-perl-5-versus-perl-6.html"&gt;blog
post on Perl 6&lt;/a&gt; led me to the description of &lt;a
href="https://www.jwz.org/doc/worse-is-better.html"&gt;Worse is better
philosophy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get the impression this idea is relatively famous, but I had not
come across it before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A summary might be, that successful systems often pass rough edges of
the design to the user, in order to avoid complexity in implementation.
This makes it harder for the user, but this is “better” because the
system is simple to implement, and therefore, is more likely to reach
the user’s computer in a state to do real work. The “worse” system gets
greater mind-share, and so it gets more attention and support.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category></entry></feed>