<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Asterisk - politics</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/feeds/politics.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://asterisk.dynevor.org/</id><updated>2024-12-01T13:44:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Co-opting suffering</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/marginal-benefit.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-12-01T13:44:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-01T13:44:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2024-12-01:/marginal-benefit.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iKgbkLcauDM"&gt;Rob
Henderson’s Nov 2024 interview at Wellesley College&lt;/a&gt;, transcribed in
&lt;a
href="https://www.robkhenderson.com/p/who-keeps-the-castle-clean"&gt;Henderson’s
substack post&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of graduates and students of elite universities will attempt to
co-opt the suffering of marginalized people. They’ll identify whatever
commonalities they share with historically marginalized groups and then
essentially co-opt the …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iKgbkLcauDM"&gt;Rob
Henderson’s Nov 2024 interview at Wellesley College&lt;/a&gt;, transcribed in
&lt;a
href="https://www.robkhenderson.com/p/who-keeps-the-castle-clean"&gt;Henderson’s
substack post&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of graduates and students of elite universities will attempt to
co-opt the suffering of marginalized people. They’ll identify whatever
commonalities they share with historically marginalized groups and then
essentially co-opt the suffering of those people, even if they
themselves haven’t suffered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They say, “Well, the category I belong to, there’s been this long
history of mistreatment.” And then from there claim that anyone who
doesn’t understand what they’ve been through or what these marginalized
communities have been through, they must be privileged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I mean, ironically, the less marginalized or the more privileged
you are, the better positioned you are to accentuate your own
marginalization because you can communicate it in a way that’s palatable
to upper-middle-class people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often what you’ll find — and I struggled with this myself, and I
speak to young people who have recently applied to college — if you’ve
truly been through something stressful or traumatic, there’s a
reluctance to speak about it. You don’t want that to be your identity.
You want to rise above it by embracing a different aspect of your
identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You want to talk about your interests or your intellectual
preoccupations or the hobbies that allowed you to distract yourself
from, or allowed you to draw your attention away from, those negative
experiences. And if you ask them to talk about those experiences, they
don’t know how to put it into words that are sort of just the right
amount of uncomfortable for the reader, the kind of Disney version of
the story rather than the real thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whereas people who have grown up relatively affluent and privileged,
and maybe they’ve experienced some mild adversity, they know how to use
the right language and the right jargon and terminology, hitting all
those right buttons so that another privileged person can read it and
say, “Okay, you’re the right kind of marginalized, you’re the right kind
of person who knows how to communicate your suffering in a compelling
way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Covid school closures, and other deviations</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/covid-school-closures-and-other-deviations.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-08-22T11:29:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-08-22T11:29:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2022-08-22:/covid-school-closures-and-other-deviations.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;What would happen if it became easy to remove anyone you choose by
using ad-hominem attacks with weak and subjective evidence?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I imagine most of us could think of some compelling examples from
history, that we would not want to emulate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a
href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/unscientific-unsafe-ableist-fatphobic-and-unethical.html"&gt;previous
post&lt;/a&gt; was about a group trying to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;What would happen if it became easy to remove anyone you choose by
using ad-hominem attacks with weak and subjective evidence?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I imagine most of us could think of some compelling examples from
history, that we would not want to emulate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a
href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/unscientific-unsafe-ableist-fatphobic-and-unethical.html"&gt;previous
post&lt;/a&gt; was about a group trying to remove a speaker at a public health
conference who had a wrong opinion on relaxing Covid restrictions. The
letter deploys various accusations of wrong-thinking against its target,
including those of being “ableist” and “fatphobic”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isn’t this bound to happen, if it works?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It certainly seems to have worked in ejecting one of the most senior
managers at the Levi-Strauss jeans company. &lt;a
href="https://www.commonsense.news/p/yesterday-i-was-levis-brand-president"&gt;Jennifer
Sey had to leave Levi’s&lt;/a&gt; when she campaigned against San Francisco
public school closures:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early on in the pandemic, I publicly questioned whether schools had
to be shut down. This didn’t seem at all controversial to me. I felt—and
still do—that the draconian policies would cause the most harm to those
least at risk, and the burden would fall heaviest on disadvantaged kids
in public schools, who need the safety and routine of school the
most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t the accepted view of the employees in her company, and in
due course, it turned out that this was just one example of her
wrong-thinking. She was also anti-science, anti-fat, anti-trans, and
racist:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;National media picked up on our story, and I was asked to go on Laura
Ingraham’s show on Fox News. That appearance was the last straw. The
comments from Levi’s employees picked up—about me being anti-science;
about me being anti-fat (I’d retweeted a study showing a correlation
between obesity and poor health outcomes); about me being anti-trans
(I’d tweeted that we shouldn’t ditch Mother’s Day for Birthing People’s
Day because it left out adoptive and step moms); and about me being
racist, because San Francisco’s public school system was filled with
black and brown kids, and, apparently, I didn’t care if they died. …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meantime, the Head of Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion at the company
asked that I do an “apology tour.” I was told that the main complaint
against me was that “I was not a friend of the Black community at
Levi’s.” I was told to say that “I am an imperfect ally.” (I
refused.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last month, the CEO told me that it was “untenable” for me to
stay. I was offered a $1 million severance package, but I knew I’d have
to sign a nondisclosure agreement about why I’d been pushed out. The
money would be very nice. But I just can’t do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sorry, Levi’s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Unscientific, unsafe, ableist, fatphobic, and unethical</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/unscientific-unsafe-ableist-fatphobic-and-unethical.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-08-17T23:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-08-17T23:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2022-08-17:/unscientific-unsafe-ableist-fatphobic-and-unethical.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A group of “public health practitioners, educators, students,
advocates, and allies” has written an &lt;a
href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1yiI9z6TS4UOFxYCmMmVb0TTqPV05HxI25BJvkC9wG50/edit"&gt;open
letter&lt;/a&gt; demanding that the American Public Health Association (APHA)
cancel an eminent speaker on public health, &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leana_Wen"&gt;Dr Leanna Wen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As they explain:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, Dr. Wen is slated to be a speaker presenting on
“Backlash,” [!] and …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A group of “public health practitioners, educators, students,
advocates, and allies” has written an &lt;a
href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1yiI9z6TS4UOFxYCmMmVb0TTqPV05HxI25BJvkC9wG50/edit"&gt;open
letter&lt;/a&gt; demanding that the American Public Health Association (APHA)
cancel an eminent speaker on public health, &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leana_Wen"&gt;Dr Leanna Wen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As they explain:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, Dr. Wen is slated to be a speaker presenting on
“Backlash,” [!] and particularly regarding misinformation. We are
demanding our colleagues and fellow leaders in public health to
reconsider and replace Dr. Wen with someone whose work is consistent
with anti-racist, anti-eugenicist public health practices and community
health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later we have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 2022 keynote is an opportunity for APHA, the foremost and largest
public health organization in the United States, to reject the history
of paternalism, eugenics, and racism and to begin rebuilding a
relationship with the public we serve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t see any evidence in the letter that Dr Wen is lacking in her
opposition to eugenics, or is in any way racist. But we do hear that Dr
Wen has some shocking views:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Wen has promoted &lt;a
href="https://twitter.com/DrLeanaWen/status/1506438947366449156"&gt;unscientific&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a
href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2022/03/21/ba2-covid-wave-concerns-restrictions"&gt;unsafe&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a
href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/politico-pulse/2022/04/22/leana-wen-stands-by-her-return-to-normal-position-00027102"&gt;ableist&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a
href="https://twitter.com/DrLeanaWen/status/1374519962136551424"&gt;fatphobic&lt;/a&gt;,
and &lt;a
href="https://twitter.com/DrLeanaWen/status/1557825060899110913"&gt;unethical&lt;/a&gt;
practices during the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s go through these one by one, by following the supporting links
given in the letter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="unscientific" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Unscientific&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evidence for “unscientific” is the &lt;a
href="https://twitter.com/DrLeanaWen/status/1506438947366449156"&gt;following
Tween by Dr Wen&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who don’t agree that the vaccinated can return to
pre-pandemic normal, I ask: What should we all do? Perpetual masking?
Forever not dining out, avoiding large weddings &amp;amp; indoor gatherings,
etc? Virtually everything has risk, and zero covid is not a viable
strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="unsafe" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Unsafe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a link to Dr Wen’s Washington Post opinion piece &lt;a
href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2022/03/21/ba2-covid-wave-concerns-restrictions"&gt;A
new Covid wave may be coming. Most Americans shouldn’t worry&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the coming weeks, the United States could see another wave of
covid-19 infections driven by a subvariant of the omicron strain, known
as BA.2. While the federal government needs to do much more to prepare
for this potential surge, most Americans should not be worried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="ableist" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ableist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is from a link to &lt;a
href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/politico-pulse/2022/04/22/leana-wen-stands-by-her-return-to-normal-position-00027102"&gt;an
article quoting Wen in Politico&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am only guessing, but perhaps the ableist sentiment is in these
passages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critics argue this isn’t her call [to urge vaccinated people to
return to normal]. People who are immunocompromised, particularly, say
that increasingly relaxed public health guidance leaves their safety out
of the equation — and they could still die from this virus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s true,” Wen told Pulse. “I think it could both be true that the
majority of individuals, if they are vaccinated and boosted, should be
able to resume pre-pandemic normal, [and] we have to do a lot more when
it comes to protecting the most vulnerable,” including more accessible
treatment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="fatphobic" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fatphobic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evidence for Wen’s fatphobia is her &lt;a
href="https://twitter.com/DrLeanaWen/status/1374519962136551424"&gt;Tweet
to Crispy Kreme&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey @krispykreme, I love that you want to thank people for getting
the #covid19 #vaccine! Every incentive helps &amp;amp; free donuts may help
move the needle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, donuts are a treat that’s not good for health if eaten every
day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s my suggestion for what to do instead: (1/4)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IPcx6e9lhag"&gt;Vinay Prasad
puts it, through barely controlled laughter&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So her tweet, that they disagree with, and these are public health
experts, is that eating Krispy Creme donut is not healthy if you do it
every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="unethical" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Unethical&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors of the letter appear to believe that advocating any
easing of precautions is, in itself, an unethical practice, to the point
that no further discussion is necessary. Here is the &lt;a
href="https://twitter.com/DrLeanaWen/status/1557825060899110913"&gt;Tweet
given as evidence for Wen’s unethical practices&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NEW: The just-released CDC guidance that eases #covid19 precautions
in schools has it mostly right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, the emphasis must shift from universal mandates to
individual decisions to minimize the disruption of in-person
learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section
id="do-you-have-any-other-insults-to-deploy-from-your-mobbing-arsenal"
class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Do you have any other insults to deploy from your mobbing
arsenal?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To count that up, the letter implies that Dr Wen’s views are in some
sense:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;eugenicist and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;racist,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and says that she supports practices that are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;unscientific,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;unsafe,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ableist,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fatphobic, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;unethical.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from the absolute absurdity of the fatphobia case, the whole
evidence for the last list appears to be that she agrees with the CDC,
and many other public health bodies across the world, that the benefits
outweigh the risks for a careful relaxation of Covid restrictions. Yes,
that’s it. That’s how you know your views are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;unscientific,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;unsafe,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ableist and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;unethical.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And maybe you’re also a racist and eugenicist. We can only
speculate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Interested in politics? Study mathematics.</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/interested-in-politics-study-mathematics.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-08-09T15:55:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-08-09T15:55:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2022-08-09:/interested-in-politics-study-mathematics.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;From Dominic Cummings’ blog: &lt;a
href="https://dominiccummings.com/2016/10/29/on-the-referendum-20-the-campaign-physics-and-data-science-vote-leaves-voter-intention-collection-system-vics-now-available-for-all"&gt;On
the referendum #20 — the campaign, physics and data science&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PPS. If you are young, smart, and interested in politics, think very
hard before studying politics / ‘political science’ / PPE at university.
You will be far better off if you study maths or physics. It will be …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;From Dominic Cummings’ blog: &lt;a
href="https://dominiccummings.com/2016/10/29/on-the-referendum-20-the-campaign-physics-and-data-science-vote-leaves-voter-intention-collection-system-vics-now-available-for-all"&gt;On
the referendum #20 — the campaign, physics and data science&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PPS. If you are young, smart, and interested in politics, think very
hard before studying politics / ‘political science’ / PPE at university.
You will be far better off if you study maths or physics. It will be
easy to move into politics later if you want to and you will have more
general skills with much wider application and greater market value. PPE
does not give such useful skills – indeed, it actually causes huge
problems as it encourages people like Cameron and Ed Balls to ‘fool
themselves’ and spread bad ideas with lots of confidence and bluffing.
You can always read history books later but you won’t always be able to
learn maths. If you have these general skills, then you will be much
more effective than the PPE-ers you will compete against. In a few
years, this will be more obvious as data science will be much more
visible. A new interdisciplinary degree is urgently needed to replace
PPE for those who want to go into politics. It should include the basics
of modelling and involve practical exposure to people who are brilliant
at managing large complex organisations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Calm capable women</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/calm-capable-women.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-08-07T09:41:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-08-07T09:41:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2022-08-07:/calm-capable-women.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Dominic Cummings, writing on the &lt;a
href="https://dominiccummings.com/2014/10/30/the-hollow-men-ii-some-reflections-on-westminster-and-whitehall-dysfunction"&gt;failures
of UK government&lt;/a&gt;, reminded me of my career as a junior doctor:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made many mistakes and was saved from the consequences of them
usually by quiet calm capable women aged 23-35 paid a fraction of the
senior management, and without whom the entire …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Dominic Cummings, writing on the &lt;a
href="https://dominiccummings.com/2014/10/30/the-hollow-men-ii-some-reflections-on-westminster-and-whitehall-dysfunction"&gt;failures
of UK government&lt;/a&gt;, reminded me of my career as a junior doctor:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made many mistakes and was saved from the consequences of them
usually by quiet calm capable women aged 23-35 paid a fraction of the
senior management, and without whom the entire [Department for
Education], and probably most of [the UK government], would
collapse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Popper against proportional representation</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/popper-against-proportional-representation.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-08-06T12:38:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-08-06T12:38:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2022-08-06:/popper-against-proportional-representation.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.economist.com/democracy-in-america/2016/01/31/from-the-archives-the-open-society-and-its-enemies-revisited"&gt;Karl
Popper argues&lt;/a&gt; that two-party first-past-the-post democratic systems
are superior to other forms of government, in that they make the
representatives and their parties more responsive to rejection by the
voters. His view of desirable government is “thoroughly practical,
almost technical” — it is a system designed to best answer the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.economist.com/democracy-in-america/2016/01/31/from-the-archives-the-open-society-and-its-enemies-revisited"&gt;Karl
Popper argues&lt;/a&gt; that two-party first-past-the-post democratic systems
are superior to other forms of government, in that they make the
representatives and their parties more responsive to rejection by the
voters. His view of desirable government is “thoroughly practical,
almost technical” — it is a system designed to best answer the question
“How is the state to be constituted so that bad rulers can be got rid of
without bloodshed, without violence?”.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Better educated, more irrational</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/better-educated-more-irrational.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-08-06T11:26:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-08-06T11:26:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2022-08-06:/better-educated-more-irrational.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Dominic Cummings on the &lt;a
href="https://www.spectator.co.uk/article/dominic-cummings-how-the-brexit-referendum-was-won"&gt;irrationality
of the well-educated&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is almost all political analysis and discussion so depressing and
fruitless? I think much has to do with the delusions of better educated
people. …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally the better educated are more prone to irrational political
opinions and political hysteria than the worse …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Dominic Cummings on the &lt;a
href="https://www.spectator.co.uk/article/dominic-cummings-how-the-brexit-referendum-was-won"&gt;irrationality
of the well-educated&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is almost all political analysis and discussion so depressing and
fruitless? I think much has to do with the delusions of better educated
people. …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally the better educated are more prone to irrational political
opinions and political hysteria than the worse educated far from power.
Why? In the field of political opinion they are more driven by fashion,
a gang mentality, and the desire to pose about moral and political
questions all of which exacerbate cognitive biases, encourage
groupthink, and reduce accuracy. Those on average incomes are less
likely to express political views to send signals; political views are
much less important for signalling to one’s immediate in-group when you
are on 20k a year. … The former live amid the emotional waves that
ripple around powerful and tightly linked self-reinforcing networks.
These waves rarely permeate the barrier around insiders and touch
others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to brother John for pointing me to this article.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Education of the heart</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/education-of-the-heart.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-08-02T13:53:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-08-02T13:53:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2022-08-02:/education-of-the-heart.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wyatt_Tee_Walker"&gt;Dr Wyatt Tee
Walker&lt;/a&gt; was a pastor, civil rights leader and anti-apartheid
campaigner. Among many other roles, he served as chief of staff to
Martin Luther King. Walker and Steve Klinsky founded the Sisulu-Walker
Charter School of Harlem. They talk about the principles and importance
of the school in the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wyatt_Tee_Walker"&gt;Dr Wyatt Tee
Walker&lt;/a&gt; was a pastor, civil rights leader and anti-apartheid
campaigner. Among many other roles, he served as chief of staff to
Martin Luther King. Walker and Steve Klinsky founded the Sisulu-Walker
Charter School of Harlem. They talk about the principles and importance
of the school in the page &lt;a
href="https://www.realclearpolitics.com/articles/2015/09/24/a_light_shines_in_a_harlem_charter_school_128189.html"&gt;A
Light Shines in Harlem&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the number of charter schools has increased, it seems that
society’s divisions along racial, religious and economic lines have only
grown wider. Anger leads to rough discourse, which leads to violence,
which leads to more anger. How can such divisions be bridged? How can
common cause be found?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer lies in education. Education of the head, and education of
the heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;… As Dr. Walker has said since 1998, charter schools and education
reform constitute the civil rights issue of our day. Equity should be
restored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even more fundamental, though, is education of the heart: the
explicit realization that every person deserves an abiding and equal
respect for the spark of divine light inside of them. This light is
innate; separate and independent from race, wealth, ethnicity or any
other identifier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, too many “remedies” – such as Critical Race Theory, the
increasingly fashionable post-Marxist/postmodernist approach that
analyzes society as institutional group power structures rather than on
a spiritual or one-to-one human level – are taking us in the wrong
direction: separating even elementary school children into explicit
racial groups, and emphasizing differences instead of similarities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is to go deeper than race, deeper than wealth, deeper than
ethnic identity, deeper than gender. To teach ourselves to comprehend
each person, not as a symbol of a group, but as a unique and special
individual within a common context of shared humanity. To go to that
fundamental place where we are all simply mortal creatures, seeking to
create order, beauty, family, and connection in a world that – on its
own – seems to bend too often toward randomness and entropy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>What is Critical Race Theory?</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/what-is-critical-race-theory.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-07-28T10:07:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-07-28T10:07:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2022-07-28:/what-is-critical-race-theory.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;These are from the standard work “Critical Race Theory: An
Introduction”, Third Edition, by Richard Delgado and Jean Stefancic
(2017).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, I’ve tried to be true the intent of the text, by
using long quotes in continuous sections, with their own headings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Page 3:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A. What …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;These are from the standard work “Critical Race Theory: An
Introduction”, Third Edition, by Richard Delgado and Jean Stefancic
(2017).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, I’ve tried to be true the intent of the text, by
using long quotes in continuous sections, with their own headings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Page 3:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A. What Is Critical Race Theory?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The critical race theory (CRT) movement is a collection of activists
and scholars engaged in studying and transforming the relationship among
race, racism, and power. The movement considers many of the same issues
that conventional civil rights and ethnic studies discourses take up but
places them in a broader perspective that includes economics, history,
setting, group and self-interest, and emotions and the unconscious.
Unlike traditional civil rights discourse, which stresses incrementalism
and step-by-step progress, critical race theory questions the very
foundations of the liberal order, including equality theory, legal
reasoning, Enlightenment rationalism, and neutral principles of
constitutional law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Page 5:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C. Relationship to Previous Movements&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the reader will see, critical race theory builds on the insights
of two previous movements, critical legal studies and radical feminism,
to both of which it owes a large debt. It also draws from certain
European philosophers and theorists, such as Antonio Gramsci, Michel
Foucault, and Jacques Derrida, as well as from the American radical
tradition exemplified by such figures as Sojourner Truth, Frederick
Douglass, W. E. B. Du Bois, César Chávez, Martin Luther King, Jr., and
the Black Power and Chicano movements of the sixties and early
seventies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Page 8:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;F. Basic Tenets of Critical Race Theory&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do critical race theorists believe? Probably not every writer
would subscribe to every tenet set out in this book, but many would
agree on the following propositions. First, racism is ordinary, not
aberrational—“normal science,” the usual way society does business, the
common, everyday experience of most people of color in this country.
Second, most would agree that our system of white-over- color ascendancy
serves important purposes, both psychic and material, for the dominant
group. The first feature, ordinariness, means that racism is difficult
to address or cure because it is not acknowledged. Color-blind, or
“formal,” conceptions of equality, expressed in rules that insist only
on treatment that is the same across the board, can thus remedy only the
most blatant forms of discrimination, such as mortgage redlining or an
immigration dragnet in a food-processing plant that targets Latino
workers or the refusal to hire a black Ph.D. rather than a white college
dropout, which stand out and attract our attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second feature, sometimes called “interest convergence” or
material determinism, adds a further dimension. Because racism advances
the interests of both white elites (materially) and working-class whites
(psychically), large segments of society have little incentive to
eradicate it. Consider, for example, Derrick Bell’s shocking proposal
(discussed in chapter 2) that Brown v. Board of Education— considered a
great triumph of civil rights litigation—may have resulted more from the
self-interest of elite whites than from a desire to help blacks. A third
theme of critical race theory, the “social construction” thesis, holds
that race and races are products of social thought and relations. Not
objective, inherent, or fixed, they correspond to no biological or
genetic reality; rather, races are categories that society invents,
manipulates, or retires when convenient. …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another, somewhat more recent, development concerns differential
racialization and its consequences. Critical writers in law, as well as
in social science, have drawn attention to the ways the dominant society
racializes different minority groups at different times, in response to
shifting needs such as the labor market. …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Closely related to differential racialization — the idea that each
race has its own origins and ever-evolving history — is the notion of
intersectionality and antiessentialism. No person has a single, easily
stated, unitary identity. A white feminist may also be Jewish or working
class or a single mother. An African American activist may be male or
female, gay or straight. A Latino may be a Democrat, a Republican, or
even black—perhaps because that person’s family hails from the
Caribbean. An Asian may be a recently arrived Hmong of rural background
and unfamiliar with mercantile life or a fourth-generation Chinese with
a father who is a university professor and a mother who operates a
business. Everyone has potentially conflicting, overlapping identities,
loyalties, and allegiances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A final element concerns the notion of a unique voice of color.
Coexisting in somewhat uneasy tension with antiessentialism, the
voice-of-color thesis holds that because of their different histories
and experiences with oppression, black, American Indian, Asian, and
Latino writers and thinkers may be able to communicate to their white
counterparts matters that the whites are unlikely to know. Minority
status, in other words, brings with it a presumed competence to speak
about race and racism. The “legal storytelling” movement urges black and
brown writers to recount their experiences with racism and the legal
system and to apply their own unique perspectives to assess law’s master
narratives. …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Wicked and dangerous fraud</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/wicked-and-dangerous-fraud.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-07-16T12:39:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-07-16T12:39:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2022-07-16:/wicked-and-dangerous-fraud.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here is a quote about American intellectual liberals from “No name in
the street” by James Baldwin, pages 29-31.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I returned to New York in 1952, after four years away [in Paris], at
the height of the national convulsion called McCarthyism. … it was a
foul, ignoble time, and my contempt …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here is a quote about American intellectual liberals from “No name in
the street” by James Baldwin, pages 29-31.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I returned to New York in 1952, after four years away [in Paris], at
the height of the national convulsion called McCarthyism. … it was a
foul, ignoble time, and my contempt for most American intellectuals, and
/ or liberals dates from what I observed of their manhood then. … I had
come home to a city in which nearly everyone was gracelessly scurrying
for shelter, in which friends were throwing their friends to the wolves,
and justifying their treachery by learned discourses (and tremendous
tomes) on the treachery of the Comintern. Some of the things written
during those years, justifying, for example, the execution of the
Rosenbergs, or the crucifixion of Alger Hiss (and the beatification of
Whittaker Chambers) taught me something about the irresponsibility and
cowardice of the liberal community that I will never forget. Their
performance then, yet more than the combination of ignorance and
arrogance with which the community has always protected itself against
the deepest implications of black suffering, persuaded me that
brilliance without passion is nothing more than sterility. … And what I
watched them do to each other during the McCarthy era was, in some ways,
worse than anything they had ever done to me, for I, at least, had never
been mad enough to depend on their devotion. It seemed very clear to me
that they were lying about their motives and were being blackmailed by
their guilt; were in fact, at bottom, nothing more than the respectable
issue of various immigrants, struggling to hold on to what they had
acquired. For intellectual activity, according to me, is, and must be,
disinterested — the truth is a two-edged sword — and if one is not
willing to be pierced by that sword, even to the extreme of dying on it,
then all of one’s intellectual activity is a masturbatory delusion, and
a wicked and dangerous fraud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Bad writing and sloppy thought</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/bad-writing.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-08-07T09:31:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-07T09:31:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2021-08-07:/bad-writing.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A link from a Washington Post article led me to &lt;a
href="https://www.orwellfoundation.com/the-orwell-foundation/orwell/essays-and-other-works/politics-and-the-english-language/"&gt;George
Orwell’s essay on Politics and the English Language&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Orthodoxy, of whatever colour, seems to demand a lifeless, imitative
style. … [Watching a political speech] one often has a curious feeling
that one is not watching a live human being …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A link from a Washington Post article led me to &lt;a
href="https://www.orwellfoundation.com/the-orwell-foundation/orwell/essays-and-other-works/politics-and-the-english-language/"&gt;George
Orwell’s essay on Politics and the English Language&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Orthodoxy, of whatever colour, seems to demand a lifeless, imitative
style. … [Watching a political speech] one often has a curious feeling
that one is not watching a live human being but some kind of dummy: a
feeling which suddenly becomes stronger at moments when the light
catches the speaker’s spectacles and turns them into blank discs which
seem to have no eyes behind them. … And this reduced state of
consciousness, if not indispensable, is at any rate favourable to
political conformity. … When there is a gap between one’s real and one’s
declared aims, one turns as it were instinctively to long words and
exhausted idioms, like a cuttlefish spurting out ink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His fundamental argument is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if thought corrupts language, language can also corrupt thought.
A bad usage can spread by tradition and imitation, even among people who
should and do know better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And later:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;.. the decadence of our language is probably curable. … What is above
all needed is to let the meaning choose the word, and not the other way
about. … .. the present political chaos is connected with the decay of
language, and that one can probably bring about some improvement by
starting at the verbal end. If you simplify your English, you are freed
from the worst follies of orthodoxy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His recipe is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol type="i"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Never use a metaphor, simile or other figure of speech which you
are used to seeing in print.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Never use a long word where a short one will do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If it is possible to cut a word out, always cut it out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Never use the passive where you can use the active.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Never use a foreign phrase, a scientific word or a jargon word if
you can think of an everyday English equivalent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Break any of these rules sooner than say anything outright
barbarous.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Quantum realm</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/quantum-realm.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-01-11T13:28:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-11T13:28:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2021-01-11:/quantum-realm.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we did on Jan. 6 in many ways was an evolution in consciousness,
because as we marched down the street along these ley lines, shouting
‘USA’ or shouting things like ‘freedom’ . . . we were actually affecting
the quantum realm”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/local/jacob-chansely-horn-qanon-capitol-riot/2021/01/09/5d3c2c96-52b9-11eb-bda4-615aaefd0555_story.html"&gt;Jacob
Anthony Chansley&lt;/a&gt; — also known as Jake Angeli. He is best …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we did on Jan. 6 in many ways was an evolution in consciousness,
because as we marched down the street along these ley lines, shouting
‘USA’ or shouting things like ‘freedom’ . . . we were actually affecting
the quantum realm”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/local/jacob-chansely-horn-qanon-capitol-riot/2021/01/09/5d3c2c96-52b9-11eb-bda4-615aaefd0555_story.html"&gt;Jacob
Anthony Chansley&lt;/a&gt; — also known as Jake Angeli. He is best known as
the man with the coyote-skin and buffalo horn headdress in the 6 January
2021 Capitol protest.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>COVID and cronies</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/covid-and-cronies.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-07-06T17:06:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-07-06T17:06:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2020-07-06:/covid-and-cronies.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have just finished reading &lt;a
href="https://guardianbookshop.com/the-covid-19-catastrophe-9781509546466.html"&gt;The
COVID-19 Catastrophe: What’s Gone Wrong and How to Stop It Happening
Again&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Horton_%28editor%29"&gt;Richard
Horton&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the title, I still don’t know what went wrong. It is
difficult to avoid the conclusion that the UK response has been among
the least competent …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have just finished reading &lt;a
href="https://guardianbookshop.com/the-covid-19-catastrophe-9781509546466.html"&gt;The
COVID-19 Catastrophe: What’s Gone Wrong and How to Stop It Happening
Again&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Horton_%28editor%29"&gt;Richard
Horton&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the title, I still don’t know what went wrong. It is
difficult to avoid the conclusion that the UK response has been among
the least competent in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found this passage from the book both tragic and pathetic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, those of my colleagues within the medical community who did
raise their voices to comment on (and, indeed, to criticize) the UK
government’s response were frequently “hammered” by more senior
colleagues who urged silence, fearing perhaps retribution in the form of
loss of government grant income, or future exclusion from powerful and
prestigious leadership roles and committees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is the result of many years of government reform.
Concentration on metrics, and money, has created a crony culture in
academia. That culture is, of course, magnificently unsuitable when we
need fast and effective action in an uncertain environment.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>US Police protect themselves from their own interrogation methods</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/laws-protect-police-from-their-own-interrogation.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-06-07T13:25:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-06-07T13:25:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2020-06-07:/laws-protect-police-from-their-own-interrogation.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the article &lt;a
href="https://columbialawreview.org/content/police-suspects"&gt;Police
suspect&lt;/a&gt;, Kate Levine discusses agreements that exist to protect many
US police forces against the same interrogation methods they use on the
rest of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;… police have dealt themselves special protections from police
questioning based on their knowledge of what protections a suspect needs
most when …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the article &lt;a
href="https://columbialawreview.org/content/police-suspects"&gt;Police
suspect&lt;/a&gt;, Kate Levine discusses agreements that exist to protect many
US police forces against the same interrogation methods they use on the
rest of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;… police have dealt themselves special protections from police
questioning based on their knowledge of what protections a suspect needs
most when facing interrogation. Meanwhile, the police continue to argue
that failing to use these selfsame tactics on other suspects will hamper
their ability to catch and convict dangerous criminals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These protections are known as Law Enforcement Officers’ Bills of
Rights (LEOBORs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LEOBORs take the form of state statutes or negotiated jurisdictional
agreements and provide affirmative interrogation protections for police
suspects that go far beyond the Fifth and Fourteenth Amendment
protections that other suspects receive. For instance, LEOBORs often
provide that police suspects may be questioned only during the day; that
they may be questioned only by a limited number of interrogators; that
they must be given time to attend to their personal needs; that they may
not be threatened, subjected to abusive language, or induced to confess
through untrue promises of leniency; and that their choice to inculpate
themselves must not be conditioned on losing their job or benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Levine points out, LEOBORS have the perverse effect of giving
greater protection from manipulation and false confession to the least
vulnerable:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[LEOBORS] further invert the purpose of constitutional protections by
giving already sophisticated suspects an extra layer of rights that the
rest of us do not receive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Despair of Twitter</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/despair-of-twitter.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-01-04T12:43:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-04T12:43:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2020-01-04:/despair-of-twitter.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;From the always-inspiring &lt;a
href="https://despair.com/collections/demotivators"&gt;Despair.com
demotivators&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virtue&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You must tweet the change you want to see in the world. It won’t
affect anything, but at least people will know exactly where you stood
during the fight. Doing nothing. Like the poser you are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the &lt;a
href="https://despair.com/collections/demotivators/products/virtue"&gt;Virtue
demotivator&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Brexit and modern art</title><link href="https://asterisk.dynevor.org/modern-brexit.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-04-03T13:40:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-04-03T13:40:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Matthew Brett</name></author><id>tag:asterisk.dynevor.org,2019-04-03:/modern-brexit.html</id><summary type="html">Brexit and modern art</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One senior Tory said [Theresa May, the British prime minister] is
"making an art form of bad misjudgements - this is not just a Reubens or
a Van Gogh, it's the whole Tate Modern". - &lt;a
href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-politics-47796013"&gt;Brexit: May
chooses a deal over party unity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tate Modern exhibits art dating from 1900. You could just imagine
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vincent_van_Gogh"&gt;Van Gogh&lt;/a&gt;
getting in under the wire, although he died in 1890. The senior Tory
being quoted does not appear to know anything about &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Paul_Rubens"&gt;Reubens&lt;/a&gt;; he
died in 1640.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"></category><category term="politics"></category><category term="brexit"></category><category term="tory"></category><category term="poor education"></category></entry></feed>